<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a printed book, intituled, Observations upon some of His Maiesties late answers and expresses</title>
            <author>Diggs, Dudley, 1613-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14255</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11844292</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11844292</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 26:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a printed book, intituled, Observations upon some of His Maiesties late answers and expresses</title>
                  <author>Diggs, Dudley, 1613-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 117 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Leonard Lichfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed by His Maiesties command"</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Dudley Diggs. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>The book being answered is an anonymous treatise, sometimes ascribed to Milton, but really by Henry Parker.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652. --  Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49803:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A PRINTED BOOK, INTITULED, OBSERVATIONS UPON SOME OF HIS MAIESTIES LATE ANSWERS <hi>and Expreſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by His MAIESTIES Command AT OXFORD, By LEONARD LICHFIELD, <hi>Printer to the Vniverſity.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1-59" type="pages">
               <pb facs="tcp:49803:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49803:2"/>
               <head>AN ANSWER <hi>TO A PRINTED BOOKE, INTITULED, OBSERVATIONS Vpon ſome of His MAIESTIES late</hi> Anſwers and Expreſſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this diſcourſe concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall authority, it is needleſſe to waſt time in declaring the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; ſince it is granted to be at leaſt mediately from God. Who intending the good of mankind, which was not to be obtained without preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of order, hath therefore commanded all to be ſubject to the lawes of ſociety, not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake: not only whil'ſt they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49803:3"/>the benefit of Governours, but likewiſe whilſt they doe ſuffer under ſome accidentall abuſes. The reaſon of which obligation may be this: we cannot reap the conſtant fruits of an eſtabliſhed policy, unleſſe by compact we ſubmit our ſelves to ſome poſsible inconveniences.</p>
               <p>Hence it follows, after a people hath by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne contract deveſted it ſelfe of that power, which was primarily in them, they cannot upon what pretence ſoever, without manifeſt breach of divine ordinance, and violation of publique faith, reſume that authority, which they have placed in another; to the end that being united in one, it may thence receive ſtrength, &amp; be enabled to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect all, as alſo to prevent thoſe fatall diviſions which attend multitudes endued with equall power, where almoſt every one upon reall or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed injuries undertakes to right himſelfe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though before poſitive conſtitution this is not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely unjuſt, yet reaſon informes us it is moſt fit by ſome agreement to part with this native right in conſideration of greater good, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of greater evills which will enſue, and to reſtraine our ſelves from being judges in our own cauſe.</p>
               <p>It followes moreover, though the people ſhould
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49803:3"/>conceave they might live more happily, if the Kings prerogative were more bounded, his reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news diminiſhed (and it is no hard matter to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to think ſo, to effect this, wants not ſo much rhetorique, as malice, ſince what is taken from the King, turnes to their preſent profit, though they oft-times dearely pay for it, by diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling their King to provide for their ſecurity) it were high ſinne to entrench upon his rights. For hereby they looſen the very ſinewes of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by receding from that compact, which craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men (out of their own private intereſts) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them they might have made more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious.</p>
               <p>It doth no way prejudice Regall authority, that <hi>God is the author of Ariſtocraticall,</hi> he may adde De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocraticall <hi>power</hi> alſo. If theſe were not lawfull formes of government, their execution of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be ſinne, and whilſt they puniſh, they would commit murder. Yet in theſe kindes, we may obſerve more or leſſe perfection, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the aptnes they beare to thoſe ends which States ayme at, which are ſafety and plenty. To haue riches, and not be able to defend them, is to expoſe our ſelves as a prey; to be ſafe, and poore, is to be ſecurely miſerable. Beſides, if we had leiſure
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49803:4"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49803:4"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49803:5"/>to look back to the Originall of Governments, we might finde that God was the immediate donor of Regall power, whereas other formes referre to him, onely as confirming the peoples Act. This the Author cunningly diſſembles, and therefore (treading in the ſteps of <hi>Mariana</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> ſworn enemies to Monarchy) he preſents us with J know not what rude multitudes, living without lawes, without government, till ſuch time, as out of the ſenſe of their ſufferings, which evidently proceeded from this want, they were inforced to fly to ſuch remedies. However this fancy might paſſe for currant among ſuch heathen Polititians as were ignorant of the originall of the world, &amp; dreamed that the firſt men were bred as Inſects, out of the mud of the earth: whence that frequent mention in their writings of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>Abori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes;</hi> yet we, who are ſatisfied with the hiſtory of the creation, cannot imagine, that Anarchy was before a regulated Government, and that God who had digeſted one <hi>Chaos</hi> into order, ſhould leave the moſt noble creatures in a worſe confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: unleſſe we will deny to <hi>Adam,</hi> either that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or providence, which is naturall and ordinary in a father over his children; and granted by this obſerver, pag. 18. to be more then the King can
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49803:5"/>challenge over his people. We find in this infancy of the world, upon the multiplying of mankinde, Colonies were ſent out, and a City was built by <hi>Cain.</hi> Thoſe long lived Patriarchs had this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, by begetting a numerous poſterity, they might people a Nation out of their own loynes, and be ſaluted <hi>Patres patriae</hi> without a metaphor; the ſame being their ſubjects and their children. In relation to this, it was properly ſaid by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, a Kingdome was but a larger family; <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> tells us, a Regall power belonged to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfamilias,</hi> and accordingly <hi>Homer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">I. 1. pol. c. 8. Odyſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q> So that it was then no more poſsible in right for ſuch a people to chooſe their rulers, then to chooſe their Fathers. Thus Regall power ſprang firſt from Paternall, and <hi>Trogus</hi> made a truer obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then this author, when he ſaid, <hi>Principio rerum</hi> (as well as <hi>gentium, nationum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>) imperium penes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges erat.</hi> And therefore may challenge more from God, &amp; nature, then other formes of government; and certainly it hath received larger elogies from God in Scripture, then any other can pretend to. To ſay nothing of the Kings of Iſrael, who are confeſt by the adverſary to be of divine inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; very heathen Monarchs are acknowledged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49803:6"/>by God himſelfe to be no leſſe. Where he calls <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadrezzar</hi> his ſervant. <hi>Ier.</hi> 43.10. and <hi>Cyrus</hi> his annointed. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 45.1. Notwithſtanding this, to the end I may give the cleareſt ſatisfaction, I have thought it fit not to take advantage from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Monarchy, whether in regard to its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity (as being not much younger then man himſelfe) or the ſeverall commodities thereof. For the truth is, it were no excuſe for ſuch endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of innovation, were it the moſt imperfect governement.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore take into conſideration this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors grounds in the method they lye, upon which he would overthrow ſo ancient and well founded a monarchye.</p>
               <p>His firſt exception is; <hi>The King attributeth the originall of his Royalty to God and the Law, making no mention of the grant, conſent, or truſt of man therein.</hi>] A groundles cavill; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God is firſt named, under what notion can be apprehend <hi>Law,</hi> but as an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the people, deriving their power, and committing the Kingdom to his truſt? within few lines he confutes himſelfe, telling us, <hi>that Law which the King mentioneth, is not to be underſtood, to be any ſpeciall ordinance ſent from heaven by the miniſtery of Angels, or Prophets, (as amongſt the Iewes it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49803:6"/>was) It can be nothing elſe amongſt Christians but the pactions and agreements of ſuch and ſuch poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique corporations</hi>] if ſo, he might have ſpared this obſervation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Dominion which is uſurped, and not juſt, yet whilſt it remaines dominion, and till it be legally againe devested, refers to God, as to it's author, and donor, as much as that, which is haereditary.</hi>] Uſurpation &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt dominion can give no right to the poſſeſſor; he that looſes a kingdome by force may recover it by the ſame title. So <hi>Athalia</hi> in the ſeventh yeare of her raigne was ſlaine by the command of <hi>Iehoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> and <hi>Joaſh,</hi> anointed King,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 11.</note> and reſtored to his right. He muſt againe anſwer him ſelfe. <hi>pag.</hi> 3. he tells us, <hi>Neither can the right of conqueſt be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to acquit Princes &amp;c. for meere force cannot alter the courſe of nature, or fruſtrate the tenour of law; and if it could, there were more reaſon why the people might justifie force to regaine due liberty, then the Prince might to ſubvert the ſame. And 'tis a ſhamefull ſtupidity in any man to think, that our Anceſtors did not fight more nobly for their free cuſtomes and lawes, of which the conquerour and his ſucceſſors had in part diſinherited them by violence and perjury, then they which put them to ſuch conflicts.</hi> Is it not a cleare contradiction to ſay that <hi>God is the author, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49803:7"/>of Dominion uſurped, and not juſt, as well as of that which is haereditary?</hi> Certainly God being Lord Proprietary of all, his donation transfers a full right to him on whom he beſtowes it. This deed of guift being knowne, it is not lawfull to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a recovery. This was the caſe of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> who after the defection of ten tribes, raiſed an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my out of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> in hopes to reduce them to obedience. But he was warned by <hi>Shemajah</hi> the man of God, not to fight againſt his brethren (not becauſe it was unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in it ſelfe, or the ſucceſſe improbable, but for that this was from the Lord.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.</note> As this was not, (ſetting aſide that extraordinary conſideration) unlawfull; So neither was it, as he is pleaſed to terme it, <hi>a ridiculous attempt, to indeavour to reduce ten tribes by the ſtrength of two.</hi> For he had raiſed an army conſiſting of one hundred and foureſcore thouſand choſen men,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 21.</note> which were warriers. And it may probably be collected from the muſter roll, which <hi>Ioab</hi> brought in to <hi>David,</hi> where the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> were 500000,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.9.</note> that thoſe two tribes were able to furniſh an army ſtrong enough to bid all <hi>Jſraell</hi> battell. Beſides as he had loſt them only by harſh language, ſo he might hope to regain them, by faire promiſes. It may be not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49803:7"/>unworthy our obſervation, what good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences did attend the defection of theſe ten tribes. Did they not preſently fall away from the true God, as well as their King, and were they not ſhortly after led into captivity?</p>
               <p>This we muſt obſerve, though force be not law, yet if after conqueſt a people reſigne their right in part or in whole, by a ſubſequent act of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they are obliged to ſtand to thoſe conditions, which they made perchance out of a probable feare of harder uſage. For the law of God gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<note place="margin">L. ſi mulier. D. quod me t. cau.</note> and the civill law in this caſe makes the Act binding. That covenants ſhould not be violated, will appeare by the revenge God took in behalfe of the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi> The children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſuffered three yeares famine, and after this ſeven of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſonnes were hanged to make an atonement for this breach of promiſe. Notwithſtanding the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites</hi> had overreached the Children of <hi>Jſraell</hi> by craft, yet they having ſworne, were bound to performe their oath unto the Lord. <hi>Doli exceptio</hi> could not take of this obligation. That they were deceived, gave no right to them to imitate what they condemned, and to deceive againe. Thus we ſee what ſpeciall care God takes to preſerve the faith of contracts. He will returne abundantly,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49803:8"/>what any mans honeſty coſts him; and therefore it is great reaſon, he that ſweareth to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſhould not diſappoint him, though it be to his own hindrance.</p>
               <p>After ſome generall truths, he comes to this iſſue. <hi>The fountaine and efficient cauſe of power is the people, and from hence the inference is juſt, the King though he be</hi> ſingulis major, <hi>yet he is</hi> univerſis minor.] This inference moſt weak: the quite contrary may clearly be concluded. The people being the efficient cauſe of power (which can be no other way but by deriving their divided power, and uniting it in him) ſince they cannot retaine what they have parted with, nor have, what they gave away, it follows he which hath all their power (I may adde his own particular beſides) muſt needs be greater and more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then they. The truth is, he is now the only fountaine of all power and juſtice.</p>
               <p>But he offers us a proofe; <hi>for if the people be the true efficient cauſe of power, it is a rule in nature, Quicquid efficit tale, eſt magis tale.</hi>] Strange that men upon ſuch palpable ſophiſtry ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to caſt of Monarchy! He will be unwilling to follow the conſequence of it. He hath an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which no queſtion he would willingly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49803:8"/>let him beſtow it upon me, he will make me rich, and himſelfe richer. For <hi>Quicquid efficit tale, eſt magis tale.</hi> I believe rather then part with his meanes, he will finde an anſwer to his own argument. By the ſame reaſon one that entreth into his ſervice, becauſe he hath made him his maſter, ſhall conclude himſelfe the better man, and challenge power over him. For <hi>Quicquid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit tale, eſt magis tale.</hi> But becauſe to prove his reaſoning abſurd, is not fully to anſwer, I will ſhew the ground of this fallacy. The axiome is true <hi>ante effectum productum,</hi> not alwaies after. So a ſparke firing a City, was once, more fire then the houſes, nor ſo after the whole towne is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one flame: or elſe thus, it is true in thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, in whom the quality by which they operate is inherent, and from whom it cannot be ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: not true in thoſe who by way of donation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt themſelves of power or wealth. Becauſe a thing can not retaine a fullneſſe, after it hath emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Jf the King be <hi>univerſis minor,</hi> then the people have placed a King not over, but under them; and they doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll to petition when they might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; they may require it from the Prince their Subject.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49803:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence it appeares that at the founding of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when the conſent of ſocieties convaies rule into ſuch and ſuch hands, it may ordain what conditions, and prefix what bounds it pleaſes.</hi>] This is moſt true; and therefore J ſhall eaſily grant, the name King to ſignifie a perſon inveſted with different power ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the varietie of lawes in ſeverall nations. His Majeſty doth moſt freely acknowledge, and will conſtantly maintain what ever rights the law doth give us; yet He is not bound to betray his own. The truth is, we ſhould be equally miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under either extreme, if the Kings prerogative ſhould ſwallow up the Subjects right, or the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects right the Kings juſt prerogative.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No diſſolution ought to be of rule convayed by the conſent of ſocietyes, into ſuch and ſuch hands, but by the ſame power by which it had it's conſtitution.</hi>] This J grant, being rightly underſtood; but becauſe the ſenſe may be eaſily miſtaken, J ſhall enlarge my ſelfe upon it. It is moſt agreeable to reaſon, that the ſame power ſhould by equall right, abrogate, as it did at firſt conſtitute. For it is not poſſible any body ſhould lay a neceſſary obligation upon it ſelfe to doe thus, when it had liberty to doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, except in relation to ſome other perſon; to whom I may part with that right I had, without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49803:9"/>poſſibility of recalling it. And this either by actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all donation, ſo when I have given away my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, J cannot challenge it as due on my repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; or by promiſe, which is an earneſt of my performance. In theſe caſes J cannot uſe my liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe it would be to the injury of another; according to that rule grounded on great equity, <hi>Nemo poteſt mutare conſilium ſuum in alterius inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L nemo D. de reg. jur.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In a popular ſtate there is but one ſimple pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and therefore the people upon conſent may eſtabliſh an Ariſtocracy, or Monarchy, when they pleaſe. But in the other two, where the authority is placed in the hands of a few, or of one, there are two parties in the contract, and therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the whole people have not any power of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving this government, unleſſe this one, or thoſe few, will voluntarily reſigne up their power into thoſe hands from which they received it; and that ſuch reſignation be not to the injury of a third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It were ſtrange if the people in ſubjecting it ſelfe to command ſhould aime at any thing but it's own good in the first and laſt place.</hi>] No queſtion, rule and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection (divided paternall powers finding it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to yeeld to one Regall, and inſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49803:10"/>to ſubmit to one common father) did ſpring from reaſon directing man-kind to its greateſt convenience. Therefore the people, ayming chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at their own good, yet perceiving this was not to be attained, except they had a common prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to adminiſter juſtice equally amongſt them, they found it neceſſary in a higher degree to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his good, in recompenſe of their ſecurity, and out of their particular eſtates, to grant to him honourable demaines, to whoſe care and juſtice, they owed the peaceable poſſeſſion of all. So the good of either is mutually involved, and that the people may be happy, they muſt firſt provide for the happineſſe of their ruler.</p>
               <p>What followes I ſhall think unworthy any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. He breaks out into a moſt ſcandalous, and falſe invective againſt the late government. That the ſubject groaned under ſome grievances, cannot be denied; and we owe to the goodneſſe of his Majeſtie, that we are free even from the feare of them for the future. J ſpeak ſincerely, what I think, though the wit of malice ſhould ſet before us the moſt exact table of all our ſufferings, (let it not impoſe upon us, what we never felt) and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare us to any other nation of the Chriſtian world, we in our worſt times were leaſt unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49803:10"/>Becauſe we have no reaſon to be in love with any evils, I ſhall not endeavour to excuſe them by compariſon with our preſent miſeries. Though neither be deſirable, yet we are too ſenſible, which we have juſteſt reaſon to complain of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hope under this word (protect) the King intends not onely to ſhield us from all kinde of evill, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote us alſo, to all kinde of Politicall happineſſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his utmoſt de voyre.</hi>] I never before did appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend in the word, <hi>Protect,</hi> this large notion; we may expect all happineſſe from His goodneſſe, we cannot challenge it from His duty. How ſhould we conceave, that the Prince is obliged by oath to take care for his people in ſuch a degree, as the moſt affectionate mother never yet took for her deareſt children. If it were ſo, then all his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royall anceſtors, who did not provide for their people in ſuch a high degree of happineſſe, as he by the adviſe of this preſent Parliament hath done, were perjured, as having all taken the oath to Protect. Every particular ſubject hath a juſt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and may challenge an intereſt in whatſoever is meant by the word, <hi>Protection:</hi> Is the King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bound to promote every particular perſon to all kinds of politicall happineſſe? to advance all to honours, offices, power, command?</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49803:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though all ſingle perſons ought to look upon the late Bills paſſed by the King as matters of Grace, with all thankfulneſſe and humility, yet the King himſelfe loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon the whole ſtate ought to acknowledge, that he cannot merit of it &amp;c. all hath proceeded but from his meere duty.</hi> It was believed heretofore, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt happineſſe of a Prince, that he was able, &amp; his greateſt glory, to be willing to oblige his people. But now he is made not capable of doing any courteſie. When he hath done all that he can, he hath diſcharged the duty of a truſty ſervant. I am confident never any age was guilty of the like ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverence, and diſreſpect to Princes, as is ſhewne in this book. <hi>If all ſingle perſons ought to look upon the late bills paſſed by the King, as matters of Grace,</hi> then they truly are ſo; for no obligation can lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a man, to believe things otherwiſe then they are. This ground deſtroyes the power of benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in a Prince, and the duty of gratitude in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. We ſhould think it very hard, if we, who are but ſubjects, ſhould be dealt with by the ſame rule. All owe a duty to their King, to their country; yet upon extraordinary ſervices we beleive, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve well of both. The example of the Houſe of Commons, will better inſtruct him, who have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times preſented their thanks, and humble
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49803:11"/>acknowledgment of his Majeſties gracious favours; and have likewiſe received thanks from moſt Counties in the Kingdome, for procuring thoſe bills ſo beneficiall to the ſubject: and yet ſurely the truſt repoſed in them, by thoſe that choſe them, and the end for which they met, did no leſſe oblige them in point of duty to doe whatſoever might conduce to the generall good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King ought not to account that a profit, or ſtrength to him, which is a loſſe and waſting to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor ought he to think that periſht to him, which is gained to the people.]</hi> By the ſame argument the people may ſhare all that he hath, and he is bound to believe, he has loſt nothing. If King and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have ſeverall rights, what law is there, which binds the King <hi>ſuo jure cedere,</hi> and enables the people to preſerve their rights, nay to challenge his? And if they have not, but the intereſts of King and people be either altogether one and the ſame, or ſo inſeparably united, as they cannot be ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then it equally follows, the people ought not to account that a profit or ſtrength to them, which is a loſſe and waſting to the King, nor ought they to think that periſht to them, which is gained to him.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49803:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regall dignity was erected to preſerve the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty.]</hi> It was ſo; for out of the ſenſe of thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, which the want of due adminiſtration of juſtice produced, routs became ſocieties, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a head over them, to whom they paid the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of reverence, for the benefit of Protection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But that which is the end is farre more honourable, and valuable in nature, and policy, then that which is the meanes.</hi>] The concluſion implied is, therefore the Commons more honourable then the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign. J will frame ſome other arguments upon the ſame principle, &amp; ſee how he approves them. Angels are miniſtring ſpirits for the good of men, but the end more honourable, and valuable then the meanes, therefore men more honourable then Angels. Once more in a cloſer paralel; Chriſt is made the head of the Church for the ſalvation of man, <hi>but that which is the end is far more honourable, and valuable &amp;c then that which is the meanes;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man far more honourable and valuable then Chriſt. If any ſhould think theſe inſtances doe not fully conclude, becauſe the higheſt end of Angels miniſtration, and the obedience of Chriſt, is the glory of God, he muſt conſider, Gods glory is the ſupream end of government alſo. And therefore this being common to both, cannot difference
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49803:12"/>the caſe. Though we grant, the good of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is more valuable, he cannot hence infer a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worthineſſe, or more power to be in them: though the ſafety of patients is moſt to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yet the Phyſitian is much better qualified to effect that end. Marriage was ordained for the lawfull procreation of children, that is honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amongſt all men, we doe not read, this is ſo. The rule doth hold in ſuch meanes, as are only va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable by that relation they beare unto their ends, and have no proper goodnes of their owne. But a King is not ſo to his people; if we looke back un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his firſt extraction, when he was taken from among the people to be ſet over them, we muſt needs behold him even then as a man of ſome worth, honour and eminency, which the ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Royalty did not deſtroy, but encreaſe. To be a meanes of his peoples preſervation, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiſtent with the height of honour. The caſe is not unlike in the nobleſt profeſſors, the Divine, the Lawyer, the Phyſition, compared to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall charges; they the meanes, theſe the ends: ſhall we from thence conclude the poore client a better man, then his learned counſell, or the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple patient, then his Doctor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This directs as to the tranſcendent</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiques,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49803:13"/>to the Paramount law that ſhall give law to all humane lawes whatſoever, and that is</hi> Salus popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li.] How many nations hath this abuſed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple brought to ruine and confuſion! It is unqueſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ionable, in the conſtitution of all Governments, this is the prime end, as being moſt agreeable with the joynt intereſt both of rulers and people. It is as much without doubt, that after eſtates eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, the governours proportion all their lawes to this end; for who that is wiſe will not provide for their ſafety, as well as he can, in whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, his own is involv'd. notwithſtanding this, the multitude (not comprehending the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which made all people commit themſelves, their lives, and fortunes to the truſt of their rulers, who were wiſer, and therefore could better fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee dangers, and had the greateſt ſhare in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, and therefore would more carefully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prevent them) readily hearken to craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men, who ſeeme to pitty their ſufferings, and tell them they are not ſo well governed as they might be. Thus <hi>Abſalon</hi> ſtole away the hearts of his Fathers Subjects. O that I were made judge in the land,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.4.</note> that every man which hath any ſuit or cauſe, might come unto me, and I would doe him juſtice. There is little good to be expected
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49803:13"/>from thoſe, who will doe wrong, that they may have opportunity to do right. Such men have great advantage on weake underſtandings, becauſe there is no ſtate wherein it might not be wiſhed that ſomethings were amended, and they preſſe upon them preſent inconveniences, and frame ſome new form, wherein they promiſe them, they ſhall be free from all, and therefore deſire their aſſiſtance in bringing this happy change a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. The people full of great hopes cry up theſe men as the only fit inſtruments of ſtate, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend only to take care for the publique, and though they have nothing, yet would be thought, not to deſire any thing. Having thus gained the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people, their next worke is to pick a quarrell with great officers (they conceave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they accuſe ſo zealouſly, it will be preſumed they are innocent themſelves) that by diſplacing them, they may make roome for themſelves. If ſuch men will not eaſily out of their preferments, the people are acquainted, theſe are the only rubs, which ſtand betwixt them and an happy govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; theſe are the cloſe enemies to the State (and ſo much the more dangerous, becauſe they carry their malignant deſignes ſo ſecretly, they cannot find proofes againſt them) <hi>Salus populi</hi> is now
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49803:14"/>concerned, the whole Kingdome is in danger; no way to ſcape this imminent perill, but by tearing theſe men from the Prince, if in a Monarchy, or putting them out of the Senate, if in an Ariſtocracy. Amongſt theſe diſtractions, and unſettlement of Government, what courſe is to be taken? The beſt way I know, (but 'tis difficult) is to make the people wiſe, and make it appeare, there is no reall danger, except from their tumultuous endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to avoyd thoſe which are imaginary. Let them rely upon their governours, who have moſt to looſe: (eſpecially if they have given them great &amp; late ſignes of their affection to &amp; care of them) this is the moſt probable way of ſafety; but if they ſhould miſcarry (which they can have no reaſon to ſuſpect) they will periſh with a great deale of diſcretion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſeemes unnaturall to me, that any nation ſhould be bound to contribute its owne inherent puiſſance, meerely to abet Tyranny, and ſupport ſlavery.</hi>] The inconveniences of Tyranny conclude nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt juſt monarchs, we are acquainted only with thoſe happy names of King and Subject. It is ſo farre from being unnaturall that any nation ſhould be bound (by which I ſuppoſe he meaneth conſent, from which an obligation naturally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49803:14"/>for it is, as with him in the Comoedy, <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate coactus ſum meâ</hi>) to contribute it's power to that end, that ſome have made it their choice, others their refuge. <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us, ſpeaking of the ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Iulius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his times, <hi>Salva eſſe Roma non poterat, niſi beneficio ſervitutis.</hi> How is it againſt nature for the Turkes to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the grand Seigneur, or the French Peſant to his Prince? There may be reaſonable motives why a people ſhould conſent to ſlavery; as if in danger of a potent enemy, they could hire none on gentler conditions to undertake their defence, or if reduced to extream want, they had not wherewith to ſuſtain themſelves, they may very probably, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> paſſe away their birthright, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. We finde an example of each caſe in holy Scripture. The Egyptians parted with all their mony, and cattle, and paſt away the right to their lands, and became ſervants to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 47.</note> upon this condition that <hi>Joſeph</hi> would afford them bread.
<note place="margin">Joſ. 9.</note> And the Gibeonites bought their lives of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael with the price of their liberty, and thought they had a cheap purchaſe.</p>
               <p>From the word truſt uſed by his Majeſty, he gathers, <hi>the King does admit his intereſt in the crown in part conditionate.</hi> No ground for this collection:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49803:15"/>for there may be a truſt, and that is ſo much the greater, if free from condition. But the thing is true <hi>de facto</hi> in ſome ſenſe, and his Majeſtie hath alwaies acknowledged, He is bound to maintain the rights and liberty of the ſubject. Yet we muſt not ſo underſtand it, as if the right to His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were ſo conditionate that it were capable of forfeiture upon a not exact performance of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for the word</hi> elegerit, <hi>whether it be future or past, it skills not much.</hi>] If he take notice of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion deduced thence he may find as much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Tenſes, as between Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, &amp; Monarchy. But the <hi>conſuetudines,</hi> which cannot refer to the future, undeniably evinces, it was meant of the time paſt, and the oath in eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh is free from all ambiguity, rendring <hi>conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines quas vulgus elegerit,</hi> by rightfull cuſtomes which the commonalty of this your Kingdome have. I may adde the different manner of the Kings anſwer as it is ſet down in their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance. Where to other queſtions which reſpect the future, the King anſwers in the future; in this as referring to what is paſt, He anſwers <hi>per verba de praeſenti, concedo &amp; permitto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King is bound to conſent to new lawes, if they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49803:15"/>be neceſſary, as well as defend the old.]</hi> His Majeſtie never thought otherwiſe; but He is not bound to an implicite faith, to believe all neceſſary, which is pretended to be ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The word</hi> elegerit, <hi>if it be in the preterperfecttenſe, yet ſhewes, that the peoples election had been the ground of ancient lawes and cuſtomes, and why the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples election in Parliament ſhould not be now of as great moment as ever J cannot diſcover.]</hi> The ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction there ſpoken of is the election of the diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, not of any repreſentative body, and that with the tacite conſent of the Prince, and ſo of much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther authority, and for the repreſentative, their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient right is not denyed, no law ſhall be abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, none enacted without their aſſent. But there is a mean between doing nothing, and all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reſult of all is, our Kings cannot be ſaid to have ſo unconditionate and high a propriety in all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects lives, liberties, and poſſeſsions, or in any thing elſe to the crown appertaining, as ſubjects have in the Kings dignity.]</hi> The King pretends not to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unconditionate proprietie in the ſubjects lives liberties, and poſſeſsions, he would onely be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowd it in his own? And what he can mean, by ſubjects having an unconditionate and high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in the Kings dignity, ſurpaſſes my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49803:16"/>It may ſeem to ſpeak this wicked do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that ſubjects may diſpoſe of the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as they pleaſe; for this right an abſolute propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety gives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the King had ſuch high right as ſubjects, it were not lawfull or naturall for him to expoſe his life and fortune for his country.]</hi> How is it lawfull for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects then to doe ſo? The people have as great, nay greater obligation of expoſing their lives for the King. This appeares by the Proteſtation, as alſo by the ancient oath of fealty at the Coronation, <hi>Je deviene voſtre Liege de vie, &amp; de biens, &amp;c.</hi> Sir <hi>Hen Spelman</hi> gives us a form of <hi>ſacramentum ligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antiae</hi> ſtill in uſe. <hi>Tu I. S. jurabis quòd ab iſta die in antea, eris ſidelis &amp; legalis (leaux) domino noſtro Regi, &amp; ſuis haeredibus: &amp; fidelitatem &amp; legalitatem (Leaultie) ei portabis de vita &amp; de membro, &amp; de ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reno honore, &amp; quòd tu eorum malum aut damnum nec noveris, nec audiveris quod non defendes (i.e. prohibebis) pro poſſe tuo, ita Deus te adjuvet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot imagine any poſsible colour for ſuch an inference; I would ſooner make a rope of ſand hang together. may not a tyrant expoſe his life in defence of his ſlave, without breach of any law? He doth but defend his owne goods,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xod 21.1.</note> for the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture calls his ſlave his money. His owne inſtance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49803:16"/>confutes him, <hi>bonus paſtor ponit vitam pro ovibus ſuis;</hi> for it is evident, this good paſtor, was our Saviour, abſolute Lord of his flock.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parliaments have the ſame efficient cauſe as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchyes, if not higher.]</hi> What, higher then the law of God and of the whole land? <hi>yes, for in truth the whole Kingdome is not ſo properly the author as the eſſence itſelfe of Parliaments.]</hi> juſt as a Proctour is the eſſence of him for whom he appeares, or an Ambaſſador is eſſentially the King: But ſuppoſe it true; this declares the materiall cauſe, proves no greater dignity in the efficient. But the reaſon is to come, <hi>by the former rule</hi> (he had no good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune with that before) <hi>'tis magis tale, becauſe we ſee ipſum quid quod efficit tale.]</hi> what, <hi>magis tale</hi> in eſſences? or can a thing be <hi>magis tale</hi> then it ſelfe? This I conceave is beyond the ſenſe of the houſe. However this confeſſion and the rule <hi>quod efficit tale eſt magis tale</hi> ſubjects the Parliament to the people, as well as the ſame rule would doe the King; and proves as well that the Parliament is <hi>vniverſis minus</hi> though it be <hi>ſingulis majus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parliaments have alſo the ſame finall cauſe as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchyes, if not greater.]</hi> what, greater then <hi>ſalus populi,</hi> nay <hi>then to promote the Subject to all kind of Politicall happines,</hi> which he told us, was <hi>the end
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49803:17"/>and duty of a King?</hi> His reaſon is, <hi>publique ſafety and liberty could not be ſo effectually provided for by Monarchs till Parliaments were conſtituted.</hi> This proves not the end higher, but ſhewes they are good helpes in government, which is readily granted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two things eſpecially are aimed at in Parliaments, not to be attained to by other meanes.]</hi> Not ſo eaſily attained indeed; but certainly many Kingdomes have enjoyed a moſt high degree of civill happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes under arbitrary Monarchs, who knew no Parliaments. Such as have abundantly ſatiſfied <hi>[the inter eſt of the people;]</hi> &amp; in all weighty affaires <hi>[adviſed with the ableſt counſellors.]</hi> Two other ends might have been named as eſſentiall as thoſe; which are to ſupply his Majeſties wants by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies, and aſſent to the abrogation of old lawes, and enacting new, as neceſſity ſhall require.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſummons of Edw.</hi> 1. (<hi>claus.</hi> 7. <hi>m.</hi> 3. <hi>dors.</hi>) <hi>we ſee the first end of Parliaments expreſſed: for he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts in the writ, that whatſoever affaire is of publique concernement, ought to receive publique approbation, Quod omnes tangit, ab omnibus approbari debet,</hi> or <hi>tractari.]</hi> I have not the convenience of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this record, and therefore cannot be able to ſatisfie my ſelfe in circumſtances, which perhaps
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49803:17"/>might afford ſome light to the cleerer underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this rule. For the preſent therefore, I will allow it to be certaine law (though he would not be willing I ſhould have the ſame liberty, and argue the legality of a thing, from a Princes bare affirmation) and ſee what advantage he can make of it. It ſeems to me to be deduced from an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent principle of reaſon, and to flow hence; it is againſt equity, that the act of one, ſhould preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice another without his conſent. There is much caution required to the managing this rule. For if it be underſtood in its full latitude, without all limitation, it will diſſolve the bonds of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by reducing us to that primitive ſtate, wherein every one had abſolute right, to diſpole of his owne as he pleaſed. Therefore we muſt take into conſideration, that multitudes finding a neceſſity of Government, did reſtraine this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive right by poſitive Conſtitutions, ſo that in the beſt governed States, the greater part of men were preſumed by a fiction of law, to handle and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove ſuch things as they never heard of. The ground of which fiction is very reaſonable; for the people though they are not adviſed with, may well be ſaid to conſent to what their rulers doe, becauſe they have entruſted them with their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49803:18"/>ſafety, which without this power convaied into ſuch or ſuch hands, could not be ſo effectually provided for. Thus in abſolute Monarchies, what Princes doe is legally the act of all: thus in our Kingdom two hundred thouſand debate and approve things by the ſuffrages of two; who many times vote quite contrary to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires who have entruſted them, and yet the people ſhall be ſaid in law to affirme, what really and in truth they doe deny. The reſult of all is this: thoſe things which the law doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſhall be tranſacted only by Parliament, the people doe handle &amp; approve of by their Knights or Burgeſſes: in thoſe things which the Law hath entruſted the King with (many of which concerne the good of the whole) what he does, is their act. Hence it may appear, the Kings Writ by which he calls the Houſes together to conſult <hi>de quibuſdam arduis &amp; urgentibus negotiis,</hi> is no waies oppoſite to this ſuppoſed Law, underſtood with due limitations. The deſire of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the Raigne of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. ſeems to mee fully to juſtify the ſame, which was, that they might not adviſe in things <hi>de queux ils n'ont pas cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance.</hi> The matters in debate were of no ſmall concernment, being no leſſe then the ſetling inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49803:18"/>commotions, guarding the marches of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and the Seas. But the anſwer is, <hi>herein they renounce not their right of conſent, they only excuſe themſelves in point of counſell, referring it rather to the King and his Councell.</hi> Here then we have the judgement of the Houſe of Commons that in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of ſome nature, and thoſe too very much concerning the ſafety of the whole Kingdome, there may be fitter Counſellors then they are. I had conceived, <hi>n' avoir pas cognizance,</hi> had not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to be ignorant, or not to underſtand things ſo thoroughly; ſince cogniſance uſes to be taken in a Law-notion, and to ſignifie a right of handling matters judicially, or power and juriſdiction, as cogniſance of Plea. We meet with a very obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſage, and which will give us great light in this buiſines; it is to be ſeen in a diary <hi>(MS.)</hi> of the Parliament held, 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>Et le lundy enſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant S. lendemayn des almes, les communes priont qu'eux ne ſoyiant pas entrez en les rolles de Parlement come parties as juggementez quex ſount donez aceſt Parlement mes la ou ils ſount in rei veritate partie et prive a cella quar lez juggementz appartient ſolement au Roy fos<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> la ou aſcun juggement eſt renduz ſur vn eſtatute feat par le comune proſitz de Royalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Le quel fuist grante.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49803:19"/>
               <p>In Engliſh thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the munday following, ſcil: the morrow after all Soules-day, the Commons prayed that they might not be entred upon the Roles of the Parliament, as parties to any judgements given this Parliament, ſave only where</hi> in rei veritate <hi>they are part and privy thereto. For that the judgements appertaine only to the King, except where any judgement is given vpon a Statute made for the common profit of the Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The which was granted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How this ſhall derogate from Parliaments either in point of conſent, or counſell, I doe not know, for at laſt they did give both, and the King would not be ſatisfied without them, and the paſſage evinces no more but this, that that King was very wiſe and warlike, and had a very wiſe Counſell of Warr, ſo that in thoſe particulars the Commons thought them most fit to be conſulted, as perhaps the more knowing men.]</hi> The concluſion which more naturally followes is this; when the King requires and will not otherwiſe be ſatisfied, they may adviſe in matters not properly of their cogniſance.</p>
               <p>The concluſion by which he thinkes he hath gained ſo much, may without any inconvenience be aſſented to. <hi>Theſe words, ad tract andum, or dinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſaciendum, doe fully prove, that the people in thoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49803:19"/>dayes were ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmoned ad conſenſum, as well as ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilium.]</hi> Be it ſo, in thoſe things which belong to their cogniſance. The formes which are uſed in paſſing a bill confeſſe ſo much: <hi>les Communes ont aſſentés,</hi> and <hi>les Seignevrs out aſſenás.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have not yee done with his rule, <hi>Quod omnes tangit, ah omnibus approbari debet.]</hi> It is true the moſt popular ſtate could never punctually obſerve it. For ſome of the poorer, &amp; ſome of the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſort, and women generally, by reaſon of their ſex are excluded, yet all thoſe, having lives to looſe, are concerned in the publique ſafety. But with what equity can he then thinke a conſiderable party of this Kingdome, can be denyed the benefit of that, which he conceives a moſt reaſonable law? I meane the Clergy, who certainly cannot deſerve to forfeit the priviledge of common men, becauſe they are more immediately the ſervants of God.</p>
               <p>His next endeavour is to ſhew that Parliaments have been much leſſened, and injuried of late by ſome paſſages in his Majeſties anſwers. But he can never make it appeare, that any part of their truly ancient power is denyed to them. The Kings words are, what the extent of their Commiſſion, and Truſt is, nothing can better teach them, then
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49803:20"/>the writ whereby they are met. We called them (and without that call they could not have come together) to be our Counſellors, not Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; for however they frequently confound them, the offices are ſeverall.</p>
               <p>The writ runs, <hi>ſuper dictis negotijs tractaturi, veſtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conſilium impenſuri;</hi> ſo that the cleare meaning is, their adviſe is not Law, except the Royall aſſent eſtabliſh it into an act.</p>
               <p>'Tis alleadged, he calls them <hi>Counſellors not in all things, but in</hi> quibuſdam arduis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the caſe of <hi>Wentworth</hi> is cited, who being a member of the Houſe of Commons, was committed by <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> but for propoſing, they might adviſe the <hi>Queen</hi> in a matter Shee thought they had nothing to doe to meddle with. He anſwers, <hi>a meere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (though of Q. Elizabeth) is no law.]</hi> It is true, a bare example ſhewes only what was, not what ought to be; but when grounded on authority, and no way excepted againſt, by thoſe, who have alwayes been earneſt defenders of their Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, it may be reckoned amongſt ſound Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: what he adds, <hi>that ſome of Her actions were retracted,</hi> is a confirmation of this; for this being out of the number, it ſeems it was accompted le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall. <hi>Exceptio firmat regulam, in non exceptis.</hi> Yet
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49803:20"/>neither did the King ſo quote this preſident as to build a right upon it.</p>
               <p>He alleadges, <hi>the King denyes the Aſſembly of the Lords and Commons, when he withdrawes himſelfe to be rightly named a Parliament, or to have any power of any court, and conſequently to be any thing, but a meere convention of ſo many private men.]</hi> This is falſly impoſed on His Majeſty; His Anſwers and Meſſages ſpeak the contrary, which are directed to both Houſes of Parliament. Beſides He hath paſſed ſome bills ſince his withdrawing. All that He affirms is that the ſole power of making or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing lawes, and altering any thing eſtabliſhed is not in them, but if He upon mature deliberation ſhal preferr the preſent government to the propoſed change, then their order is not to have the force of law, and oblige the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The <hi>King is ſaid to aſſert, that becauſe the law hath truſted him with a prerogative to diſcontinue Parliaments, therefore if He do diſcontinue Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to the danger or prejudice of the Kingdome, this is no breach of that truſt, becauſe in formality of law, the people may not aſſemble in Parliament but by His writ.]</hi> This is groſſe forgery: if it appeare to him neceſſary or expedient for the Kingdom, He acknowledges He is obliged by that truſt repoſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49803:21"/>in him to iſſue out his writs. And to this end He gratiouſly ſigned the bill for a trienniall Parliament; which like Phyſick well timed, may preſerve the body of this ſtate in health and ſtrength, by not ſufferring ill humors to grow to any head.</p>
               <p>Another aſſertion of the Kings he ſaies is, <hi>if the Parliament make any tranſition in other matters, then what he pleaſes to propoſe, they are lyable to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment at his pleaſure.</hi> All this he collects from the citation of <hi>Wentworths</hi> caſe. The ſence of his inference is this; becauſe they cannot juſtify the medling with things which belong not to their cogniſance, therefore they may be puniſht, if they medle with thoſe that do. We may obſerve an affected miſtake in this author, of which he makes frequent uſe; and this animadverſion though once laid down, may often be applyed. Whatſoever the Houſes do, he calls that, the Act of the people. Whereas the truth is, they repreſent them only to ſome purpoſes, and ends. So that if they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed their commiſsion, and vote things not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their cogniſance, the People by no meanes is engaged in it, as having no legall way of expreſsing themſelves in ſuch caſes.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty clearly to prove, that the truſt committed to both Houſes, cannot bind Him to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49803:21"/>aſſent, to what ever they propoſe, ſeem it of never ſo dangerous conſequence to the Kingdom; nor abſolve Him in point of conſcience, if His rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tell Him, His people will extreamly ſuffer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the grant, argues thus. It is impoſsible that the ſame truſt ſhould be irrevocably committed to Us, and Our heires for ever, and the ſame truſt, and a power above that truſt, (for ſuch is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer they pretend) be committed to others: did not the people, that ſent them look upon them, as a body but temporary, and diſſoluble at Our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? and can it be beleived, that they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for Our Guardians and comptrollers in the managing of that truſt, which God and the law hath granted to Us and Our poſterity for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</p>
               <p>Strange it is, that affection ſhould ſo blinde the underſtanding, and worke mens beliefe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon but deſire! I muſt needs think the let lies only in his will, elſe he could never ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy himſelfe with ſuch weak anſwers. <hi>It is true,</hi> faith he, <hi>two ſupreames cannot be in the ſame ſence and reſpect.]</hi> If he had not hoped to hide himſelfe in generalls, he would have deſcended to particulars, and told us, in what ſence, what reſpect, and what matters the King was ſupream, in what the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49803:22"/>two Houſes. But an application would have diſcovered the truth, even to weak underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nothing is more knowne, or aſſented to, then this, that the King is</hi> ſingulis major, <hi>and yet</hi> univerſis minor.] I have already evidenced the contrary; yet I will ſpeak ſomething to it here. By <hi>univerſis</hi> he muſt mean the repreſentative all, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he concludes to be above, and have greater power then the King, that is ſuch a power as He is bound to obey. So it ſeems the King hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the oath of allegiance as well as we, and we may call Him, our fellow ſubject. <hi>Yet the oath of Supremacy</hi> he tells us, <hi>is no waies endangered.]</hi> The ſenſe of his reaſon is, becauſe <hi>he is a better man then any one of us, take us ſingle.</hi> He tels us He is better then any one, He does not tell us, He is better then two; if the Kings ſupreamacy be no more but this, it is no more then poſsibly He might have and probably had before He was King. It is not the Prince <hi>ſingulis major?</hi> nay may not any Lord in the Land challenge the ſame ſupreamacy over all the Knights, any Knight o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all eſquiers to be <hi>ſingulis major,</hi> though <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſis minor?</hi> But perhaps ſome othes limitation may be found out; the meaning ſhortly ſhall be,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49803:22"/>that he is above the Pope in theſe his dominions, not but that He is under His ſubjects. to take of theſe and all other corrupt gloſſes, I ſhall refer him to <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>vices,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Hen</hi> 8. In the preface of which ſtatute the Kings ſupreamacy (not over ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) but the body Politique is clearly delivered. The words are theſe; <hi>Where by divers, ſundry, old, authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick hiſtories &amp; chronicles, it is manifeſtly declared &amp; expreſſed, that this Realm of England is an Empire and ſo hath been accepted in the world, governed by one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream head and King, having the dignity and Royall eſtate of the Imperiall Crown of the ſame: unto whom a Body Politique, compact of all ſorts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of people, divided in tearmes, and by names of ſpiritualty and temporalty, been bounden and owen to beare next to God, a naturall and humble obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there were no King at all in England, you would call this government an Ariſtocracy; and why I beſeech you do you not confeſſe that name now, ſeeing the thing is altogether the ſame? for if they give his voice, tis all one, as if he had no voice, if their power muſt over-rule his, tis all one, as if he were deveſted of all, nay, why is it thought fit to ſend to him and ſollicite his conſent, when it is legally paſt in that the two houſes have voted it? why to all publique bills do they require this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49803:23"/>
                  <hi>Le Roy Le voet?</hi> (is it only for the ſame reaſon that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> gives why the Pope being alone infallible, calls generall councells, <hi>ut res ſuavius tranſigatur?</hi>) ſuppoſe he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne in anſwer, that of SENECA, <hi>Si vultis ſcire an velim, efficite ut poſsim nolle.</hi> Thus though he plead for a new government, he is aſhamed to own it by the right name. For he tells us, not without ſome indignation at the very thought of ſuch an innovation. <hi>This new Aristocraticall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brique cannot ſeem to any impartiall man, but as emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a ſhadow, as airy a dream as ever mans fancy abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it ſelfe withall.</hi> I dare ſay he cannot meet in all hiſtories, and records (except of ſuch Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as have depos'd Kings, which he confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no free one ever did) with one example of this nature, that the two Houſes ſhould pretend to a power, which muſt of neceſsity over-rule the King. Indeed a reaſonable man cannot imagine, any preſident poſsible, becauſe, ſince the law hath given the King a power, by diſſolving the Parliament, to take away that power (as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) greater then his own, if they had ever made claim to ſuperiority over him, he would quickly have put an end to that diſpute. Before this power be challenged, it would befit, to vote
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49803:23"/>down, that clauſe in a law made 2. <hi>Hen.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cited by His Majeſty, <hi>that it is of the Kings regality to grant or deny ſuch of their Petitions, as pleaſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding this, he muſt be UNIVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIS MINOR, <hi>for this wee ſee in all conditionate Princes, ſuch as the Prince of Orange &amp;c.</hi> I never knew he had Regall power before. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance abundantly manifeſts his deſigne, though he is pleaſed to ſay, <hi>he ſpeakes nothing in favour of any alteration, but is as zealouſly addicted to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, as any man can, without dotage.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the moſt abſolute Empire in the world, this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is most naturall and neceſſary, that the ſafety of the people is to be valued above any right of his.]</hi> It is againſt common ſenſe to ſuppoſe a King that is in his wits, (me thinkes all good people ſhould take to heart thoſe deſperate concluſions, which are built upon moſt unreaſonable and moſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſuppoſitions of a King that is mad, or a child; ſince never ſubjects had greater obligation to be thankfull to Allmighty God for giving them a Prince as eminently able, as vertuous) who will not provide for the ſafety of His people, nay who will not part with ſome of His right, rather then they ſhould periſh, becauſe in their deſtruction
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49803:24"/>He looſes all. Yet this does not prove a King ſhould part with His rights, as often, as they will pretend to be in danger. If this were once admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what wild plots would be invented, what ſtrange intelligence would be received from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible ſpyes? and as often as crafty men were am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious or covetous, ſo often the filly people were to be frighted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since all naturall power is in thoſe which obey, they which contract to obey to their owne ruine, or having ſo contracted, they which eſteeme ſuch a contract before their owne preſervation, are felonious to themſelves and rebellious to nature.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He cannot mean any people contracting to their own certain ruine; there never was govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, guilty of this madnes: therefore He muſt underſtand a contract to a poſſible ruine; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, an agreement patiently to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ordinary tryall of Law, and to ſuffer, if it ſhould ſo fall out, though under an undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſentence. In this caſe, he that does not make reſiſtance, and prefer his preſervation to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, is pronounced <hi>felo deſe,</hi> and a rebell to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Unhappy thiefe, who for felony is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be hang'd, and will be guilty of another felony in being hanged! what way is left unto
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49803:24"/>innocency? He muſt kill as many as he can in His own defence, ſo ſhall He eſcape, or dye in the quarrell; either way He hath done right to nature. Let us put another caſe; an innocent man by the ordinary courſe of juſtice is adjudged to dye, upon the teſtimony of two bearing falſe witnes: he was free from fault before; now he is in ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, except he refuſe to be puniſht, he becomes guilty, no leſſe then a ſelfe murderer. I wonder what opinion this man hath of Martyrs, who va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew not their owne preſervation; can he think by ſubmitting themſelves to one fire, they deſerve to be caſt into another? nay, what of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? who certainly ſuffered moſt injuriouſly, &amp; though he had ſtrength enough to preſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and could have been aſsiſted by an Army of Angells, yet he was obedient to death. I cannot imagine from what principle he ſhould draw ſuch a concluſion, unleſſe it be from this, (whence indeed moſt of his book will naturally flow,) that there is no ſuch thing as juſtice, but <hi>ſuprema lex,</hi> the paramount law, is profit; and the faults of men conſiſt, in the not violation of contracts, in the not breaking promiſes, if they be for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage: for it were a ſinne againſt native liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to make our ſelves the ſlaves of juſtice.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49803:25"/>
               <p>If we examine the ground of this doctrine moſt deſtructive of all commerce, all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we ſhall diſcover it to be no other but this, that the law of nature doth allow a man to defend himſelfe, and provide for his owne preſervation. But the obſerver takes no notice, that it is in our power to part with this right, &amp; yet doe nothing contrary to nature, if reaſon tell us, we ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by obtaine a more excellent good, the benefit of peace and ſociety; nay, that this reſtraining Our ſelves by compact of that naturall liberty to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelves, will conduce more, to that end, for which it was given us, our preſervation and ſafety. Becauſe in probability, we ſhall be in leſſe danger, living amongſt men who have agreed to be governed by certaine lawes, then if every one followed his owne inclination. Where one ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers hereby wrongfully, thouſands enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of being protected from wrong. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though it ſhould happen to me in particular, to be condemned by the magiſtrate without cauſe, I am bound to ſuffer patiently, becauſe having made ſuch a bargain, which might have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, I have no right to recall it, when it appears diſadvantageous. I owe, that I have been ſafe thus long to the benefit of this covenant, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49803:25"/>am bound in juſtice to ſhare the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. If reaſon will not ſatisfie, perhaps Chriſtianity may. <hi>Qui reſiſtunt poteſtati,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>ipſi ſibi damnationem acquirunt.</hi> To reſiſt the magiſtrate, damnable. The powers here ſpoken of, were heathen, yet Chriſt commanded his, to be ſubject even to them. That anſwer (with which too many are deceived) cannot excuſe diſobedience, and Rebellion; This precept obliges private men, but not magiſtrates. Since inferiour magiſtrates being oppoſed to the ſupreame power are but as private men, and in this reſpect the reaſon of obedience is common to both. Neither is this a hard law, if duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. If we ſuffer juſtly, we have no reaſon to complain: if undeſervedly, we are puniſhed, but not hurt. The magiſtrate is <hi>Dei miniſter nobis in bonum,</hi> becauſe God will abundantly reward us for our patient ſuffering in obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>But this is against nature.]</hi> He muſt mean nature guided by right reaſon; and doth that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, that rather then part with a temporall life, we ought to forfeit an eternall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is objected that a temporary power, ought not to be greater, then that which is laſting and vnalterable.]</hi> He does not frame the Kings argument aright; which concludes on this ground, that it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49803:26"/>the lawes ſhould place a power greater then his in ſuch a body, and yet leave it to his diſpoſall, when to call that body together, when to diſſolve it; that is, to determine, when and how long he would be over-ruled, &amp; when be King again. His Majeſty preſſes it farther (which he diſſembles.) This truſt being irrevocably committed to Him and His heires for ever, it cannot be conceived, how it ſhould ſleep, during the ſitting of the Houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if this were ſo, the Romans had done unpoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquely, in creating Dictators, when any great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity aſſailed them and yet we know it was very proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to them, ſometimes to change the form of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.]</hi> Hence we may conclude it good policy, in imminent danger, to truſt to a Monarchy, not an Ariſtocracy, and much leſſe to a democracy. The Romans ſucceſſe cannot be imputed meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their change, but to this, that they altered their form from worſe to better, (as to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ends) but that will not juſtifie his deſire of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation from better to worſe.</p>
               <p>It is further objected, He ſayes, if we allow the Lords and Commons to be more then counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, we make them Comptrollers, and this is not ſuitable to Royalty. He anſwers, <hi>we ſay here, that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49803:26"/>to conſent is more then to counſell, and yet not alwayes ſo much, as to command and comptroll.]</hi> True, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes; but then it is, when their conſent ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a neceſſity upon the King of doing the like. He hath not laid down his Majeſties words faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. The point He ſtands on is, that their adviſe, is not His law, neither is He bound to captivate His reaſon, or ſubmit His conſcience to their Votes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, it must be ſo; becauſe in inferiour Courts, the Judges are ſo counſellors for the King, as that the King may not countermand their judgements, and yet it were a harſh thing to ſay, that they are therefore Guardians and Comptrollers of the King; therefore it holds in Parliaments</hi> a fortiori.]</p>
               <p>The reaſon why the King cannot countermand their judgement, is becauſe they ſuſtain His per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and His conſent is by law involv'd in what by law they do, and there would be no end, if He ſhould undoe what He hath done. <hi>Authoritas rei judicatae vim legis habet;</hi> there can be no appeal from himſelfe to himſelfe. He therefore makes the Judges take an oath, they will deny to no man common right by His letters, becauſe He is not to paſſe ſentence in private, but in publique and in a Judiciall way. That it is his owne act, appears
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49803:27"/>from this, that He delegates his power to them, and this is a known rule, <hi>Quod Rex facit per offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciarios, per ſe facere videtur.</hi> The truth is Kings have a right, and heretofore they made uſe of it, to ſit in judicature perſonally. <hi>Camden</hi> tells us, that <hi>Bancus Regius ita dictus erat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rit. 112.</note> 
                  <hi>quòd Rex ipſe in eo praeſidere ſolebat.</hi> Sir <hi>Tho: Smith</hi> too in his deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of England, <hi>Subſellia Regia (vulgo Bancus Regius) ex eo ſortita ſunt appellationem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">l. 2. c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>quia ibi ipſi Angliae Regesſedere conſueverunt.</hi> This Court was called the Kings Bench, becauſe the King ſate as judge in it in His proper perſon. It removed with the King, as is to be ſeen 9. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. by which the Court of common Pleas is fixed. <hi>Common pleas ſhall not follow our court, but ſhall be holden in ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover the Judges ſwear, they will <hi>not aſſent to any thing which may turne the King in damage, or diſheriſon, by any manner, way, or colour.</hi> 18. <hi>Edw:</hi> 3. when he can make theſe things agree to the two Houſes, he ſhall conclude from the Iudges ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to their votes. But ſince it will clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that they are not the mouth of the King, the Lords ſitting in a perſonall capacity, and the Houſe of Commons as repreſenting the body of the Kingdom (though not that to all intents and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49803:27"/>purpoſes) the inference muſt by no means be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I ſhall adde this to make the anſwer more clear, and to avoid miſtake: in matters of Law, there lyes an appeal to them, a writ of errour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought, as to the higheſt Court; not ſo in matters of ſtate. Becauſe whilſt they paſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence according to known lawes, the ſtate is no way indangered thereby, but if they challenge to themſelves a liberty of paſſing ſentence according to reaſon of ſtate, they may when they pleaſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw our lawes. The Counties which intruſted them looke upon them as Judges, not Politicians.</p>
               <p>But <hi>we ought not to conceive, that they well either Councell, or conſent to any thing, but what is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely advantagious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the King conceives they do not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, He will moſt willingly follow their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe. This fallacy (though extreamly weak) hath influenced on all his book. He takes the two Houſes in ſuch a Notion as not failing of their duty, but doing every thing as they ought, and ſuppoſeth the King to be wanting to that truſt which is committed to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By ſuch Councell and conſent we cannot imagine the King limited or leſſened.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such a Conſent, in which his is neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49803:28"/>renders his Power not ſo properly leſſe as none at all, it doth not limit, but take it away. Pray put the Caſe, a thouſand pounds is left to <hi>Titius</hi> and <hi>Sempronius,</hi> to be beſtowed upon joynt conſent, <hi>Sempronius</hi> being juſt and reaſonable grants to <hi>Titius</hi> the right of a Negative, ſo that without he will concurre, he confeſſes he can doe nothing, (The King doth not pretend to have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of repealing old or conſtituting new Lawes without them) <hi>Titius</hi> not content with this Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, affirmes <hi>Sempronius</hi> is bound to conſent to what ever he thinks fit; if ſo, is not this money wholely at <hi>Titius</hi> his diſpoſall? Can any one be ſo ſtupid as to tell <hi>Sempronius</hi> notwithſtanding this, He hath a full power? How did ſhip-money de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our propriety, but by this very conſequence? Law and Reaſon informe us, that <hi>Ejus eſt velle qui poteſt nolle.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>L. in bello.</hi> §. <hi>medio. D. de cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiv. &amp; poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim.</hi>
                  </note> Hence <hi>Tryphonius</hi> determines that a Captive cannot conſent to his ſonnes Marriage. Why? <hi>Cum uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nec diſſentire poſſet.</hi> And <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is alledged in derogation of Parliaments: that whatſoever the right of Parliaments is, to aſſemble or treate in all caſes of a publicke nature, yet without the Kings concurrence and conſent, they are liveleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions without all vertue and power, the very name
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49803:28"/>of Parliaments is not due to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this Man had a mind to deale candidly, he would deliver the Kings ſenſe truly, and let Him ſpeak His own words. The ſumme of which is onely this, the two Houſes have not power of making lawes and altering the eſtabliſhed gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But this Allegation at one blow confounds all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and ſubjects us to as unbounded a regiment of the Kings meere will, as any Nation under Heaven ever ſuffered under.]</hi> Very tragically expreſſed and with high confidence, but not any colour of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For are we not left in the ſame ſtate in which we were? His Majeſties denying to bring in a new government, doth not take away the old. If He thinke it not convenient to alter that forme which the leaſt deceitfull Argument, long experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence under ſo many of His glorious Anceſtors hath proved happy, can any who is not in love with error inferre hence, this ſubjects us to a lawleſſe and moſt unbounded regiment?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon the ſame reaſon by the Kings deſertion other Courts muſt needs be vertueleſſe and void.]</hi> It were a ſtrange conſequence to conclude that, becauſe that may be done without the King, to which His conſent by law is not required, therefore that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49803:29"/>may be done without him, to which his conſent is by law neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Many Kings have diſſented from Bills, yet the people were never ſo mad, as to feare a deſertion of all Courts. It is againſt common ſenſe to fancy that He which enjoyes all by the benefit of Laws, ſhould hinder the due adminiſtration of Juſtice according to thoſe Lawes, ſo willfully endanger, not onely his rights, but ſafety, by putting His Kingdome into tumults and combuſtion. Every wiſe man may have as ſtrong ſecurity, he ſhall not ſuffer from the (onely not impoſsible) execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a power, becauſe it is ſo manifeſtly deſtructive of the Kings own intereſt (and made evident to be ſo as well by experience as by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) as any man can have reaſon, not to be afraid of himſelfe, becauſe he hath a full power over himſelfe and may deſtroy himſelfe, when he pleaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The intent of the King is, that the great Aſſembly of the Lords and Commons doe not repreſent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Right of the whole Kingdome, or elſe that there is no honour nor power, nor Iudicature reſidering in that great Majeſticall Body, then which ſcarce any thing can be more unnaturall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A moſt impudent collection, the meaning in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49803:29"/>breife is onely this, when the particular conſents of three are neceſſary, it's not in the power of any two, to effect whatſoever they pleaſe. A moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent eſtabliſhment in favour of preſent govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: that we may have no innovation without the mutuall agreement of King and people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is attempted to divide further between part and part in Parliament.</hi> Who theſe attempters are, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not. I ſuppoſe he meanes thoſe who devided the Lords into good and bad, the Members of the Houſe of Commons, into well, and ill affected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So making the major part not fully concluding.</hi> They are not denyed to conclude as far as the power of that Houſe extendeth, but this cannot reach to an abſolute and finall deciſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a wonderfull thing that the King's papers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fraited ſcarce with any thing elſe but ſuch doctrines of diviſion,</hi> ('tis more wonderfull that in a well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned ſtate ſuch diſreſpectfull language of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from private pennes ſhould paſſe unregarded, unpuniſhed) <hi>tending all to the ſubverſion of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fundamentall conſtitutions, which ſupport all our ancient liberties, and to the erection of Arbitrary rule, ſhould find ſuch applauſe in the world.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a vaſt difference between declaring what diviſions are, and cauſing them to be; to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49803:30"/>ſhew, is not to teach diviſion. But it is beyond admiration, if the King's aimes are ſuch, as He would have the world beleeve, that they ſhould find ſuch applauſe. Eſpecially if we conſider the perſons from whom; men that have much more to looſe, then ſome who may ayme at getting greater fortunes, by pretending they are in danger to looſe what they have: Men that are knowen not to value their lives equall to their liberties; men of as great wiſdome, as honeſty, neither of which would permit them to be active to make themſelves miſerable, and pull upon their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Countrey perpetuall ſlavery. What impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of malice is it, to accuſe the King to intend that, when the world ſees how much He hath ſuffered meerly to prevent it? Could our Anceſtors ever have beleeved there ſhould come a King, who would plead for <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> who would hazard His Crown in defence of the ſubjects Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and deſire nothing more, then the utter abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of all Arbitrary rule?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the King have parted from his Parliament meerely becauſe they ſought His oppreſsion, &amp; He had no other means to withſtand their tyrany, Let this proclaim them a voyd aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Majeſty never layd ſuch charge to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49803:30"/>yet it is moſt evident there was too great reaſon elſewhere to juſtifie His feares; when not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding His deepeſt Proteſtations to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the true eſtabliſhed Religion, they ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Him inclining to Popery; when not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding His utmoſt endeavours to ſuppreſſe that unhappy Rebellion in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and after the Houſes had taken that worke into their care, His frequent preſsing them to ſend over ſufficient ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes, and not to ſpend their time in buſineſſes of little moment, whilſt their poore Brethren were dayly butcherd, yet the people were made beleeve He was a favourer of their bloody deſignes; when the baſer ſort of the people were permitted to come even to the Parliament, in Clamarous, and unwarrantable multitudes, and there was a kind of diſcipline in diſorder, tumults being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at command, upon a watch-word given; when ſeditious Pamphlets hourely came out, and many Preſſes laboured day and night to abuſe the King; when factious Preachers were incouraged, whilſt they did caſt publick obloquies on the Lawes which ſtood in full force, and which if they had been duly executed, would have juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, by reſtoring Us to our former Peace and happineſſe, which We ſo long injoyed,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49803:31"/>as We knew how to obey; when ſuch ſeditious fellowes out of their Pulpits did dare to ſtrike even at the higheſt, and with more boldneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with leſſe danger, as meaning to fight with other mens hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the King could be more wiſely or faithfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by any other Court, or if His ſingle judgment were to be preferd before all advice whatſoever; it were not onely vaine but extreamly inconvenient that the whole Kingdome ſhould be troubled to make elections, and that the parties elected ſhould attend the publike buſineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are other Ends beſides this for which they are called together, yet this is one main end, as appears by the Kings writ, and therefore He never refuſed to adviſe with them. The uſuall (but not the onely) forme of the Kings Anſwers to ſuch Bills as they were not willing to paſſe (which I beleeve was never objected to any Prince before to His Majeſty) <hi>le Roy s' aviſera,</hi> proves that after the advice of this His great Councell, He is yet at liberty to adviſe further with perſons or occaſions, as His owne wiſdome ſhall think meet. But this Author will by no meanes take notice, that the uſe of Counſell, is to perſwade, not to compell: as if a man in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49803:31"/>of great concernment, might not very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conſult with many friends, and yet at laſt follow the advice perhaps of one, if it appeare more proportionable to the end he aymes at.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not ſo, becauſe the many eyes of ſo many choiſe Gentlemen out of all parts, ſee more then fewer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Argument, I beleeve will conclude too much, and therefore nothing at all. For the ſame reaſon which denyes a liberty of diſſenting to the King, (that is ſuch a number, who ſee more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are more) may deny it to the Houſe of Pears, in compariſon of the Houſe of Commons, and to that Houſe too, in compariſon of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſo both King and Lords and Commons are voted out of Parliament. Beſides experience ſhews this rule is not generally true, for I dare ſay if we ask almoſt any Parliament man, he will tell us, upon the reading of a Bill, ſometimes one man in the Houſe hath found more faults, and urged more juſt exceptions, then three hundred would have been able to eſpy. There have been Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherein Acts have been made to remedy former miſtakes. Nay, whole Parliaments have been repeal'd and declared <hi>Null</hi> by ſucceeding Parliaments, ſo 21. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. does voyd and diſanull all the Statutes made in a former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49803:32"/>held 11. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. ſo 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. repeales this whole Parliament of 21. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. So 39. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. In a Statute made at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> We find a totall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal of a Parliament held at <hi>Coventry</hi> the yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as made <hi>againſt all good faith and conſcience, &amp;c: the Acts and Statutes laboured by the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, procurement and excitation of ſome ill diſpoſed Perſons for the introduction and accompliſhment of their rancour and inordinate Covetiſe.</hi> So 49. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. A Parliament held at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> is made Null, in regard diverſe matters had there been treated and wrought <hi>by the laboured exhortation of Perſons not fearing God, nor willing to be under the rule of any earthly Prince; but inclined of ſenſuall appetite to have the whole governance of the Realme under their owne power and domination.</hi> Theſe are the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that one great Councell beſtowes upon another.</p>
               <p>I could urge the ſame Arguments, in the very ſame words, onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anging a Lay-councell, into an Eccleſiaſticall Councell, and upon equall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity, require the King to aſſent to what ever they ſhall vote. I make no doubt, the Author will in this caſe give him leave to make his conſcience his guide, and if he doe, he will think his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments deſerve no further anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59-117" type="pages">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:49803:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The few private ends they can have to deprave them muſt needs render their counſells more faithfull, impartiall, and religious then any other.]</hi> Certainly they may have as many, as any other private Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and that this Kingdome hath ſeldome here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſuffered under the proſecution of private intereſt is to be imputed to the excellent policy, which he endeavours to overthrow. They are ſtrangely tranſported with the love of a popular ſtate, who can ſo overrule their underſtandings as to force themſelves to think the members of it may not be extreamly ſubject to <hi>ambition,</hi> which would eaſily prompt them to alter the good old wayes of beſtowing Offices, and collating Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; to <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> which would tempt them to draw the determination of cauſes out of the ordinary Courts of Iuſtice; to <hi>hatred,</hi> which would make them proſecute their enimies with bitter violence, and upon the leaſt ſuſpition of a fault, to puniſh them firſt by impriſonments, and to prove them guilty at leaſure; to <hi>affection,</hi> which would make them ſhield their friends from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing queſtioned, though their corruptions were notorious to all the world.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> his caſe ſpeaks home to the buſineſſe, we are told in the 3. c. of the 2.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49803:33"/>Parliament held 1. <hi>Mar.</hi> how the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> was diſſolved in a former Parliament, 7. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. which was <hi>compaſſed, and brought to paſſe, by the ſinister labour, great malice, and corrupt means of certain ambitious perſons, then being in Authority, rather for to enrich themſelves, and their friends with a great part of the poſſeſsions of the ſaid Biſhoprick, then upon juſt occaſion, or Godly zeale.</hi> Let the world judge, whether this Age may not be ſubject to the ſame temptation, and whether a deſire to ſhare the means of the Church may not have as ſtrong operations as formerly.</p>
               <p>Nothing more common in the Roman ſtory then the bribing of the Senate. This made <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurtha</hi> cry out (who by his guifts governed their Parliament) <hi>O Vrbem venalem &amp; maturè peritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, ſi emptorem invenerit!</hi> Had it been our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſſe to have lived in a popular ſtate (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they are altered from what Hiſtories deliver them) we ſhould have found injuſtice a trade, and that the moſt compendious way to wealth was to buy no land, but of the Judges. <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives us a full character of what we might well feare. When the government of <hi>Rome</hi> was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a Monarchy under <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were very well contented <hi>Suſpecto Senatûs
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49803:33"/>populi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> imperio, obcertamen Potentium, &amp; avariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Magiſtratuum: invalido legum auxilio, quae vi, ambitu, postremò pecuniâ turbabantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They muſt evidently have more private ends then the King, who may be miſlead upon wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, but they muſt ſtruggle with ſolid temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, deſire of riches, deſire of honours, there being an emptineſſe in them, whereas He is full and ſatisfied. <hi>Si violandum eſt Jus, regni causâ vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landum eſt;</hi> the greateſt motive that can be, a hope to ſhare in Soveraignty, the Parliament to rule the King and they to rule the Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We have ever found enmity and antipathy betwixt the Court and the Country, but never any till now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the repreſentatives and the body of the Kingdom repreſented.]</hi> How betwixt them and thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that intruſted them? are not they ſatisfied with their carriage? If this were never till now, it may ſeem to be upon ſome cauſes, which never were till now.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hollis <hi>his rich Widdow, I never heard that promotion came to any man by ſerving in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>] What ſervice commended M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hollis</hi> to the rich Widdow I cannot judge, this I know, if the <hi>ninteen propoſitions</hi> had paſt, it would have been no newes to heare of many promoted, and they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49803:34"/>might eaſily have redeemed the time that they have loſt, and challenged ſo much greater ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, becauſe they could not have them ſooner. It would have been rare, to have heard of any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced out of Parliament, &amp; this would have bred good ſtirring blood in the Countrey, the Gentry would have juſtled to get in at the common gate of Offices and Honours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lords and Commons ought not to be deſerted, unleſſe we will allow, that the King may chuſe whether He will admit of any Councell at all or no, in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our Lives, Lands and Liberties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Law He cannot, He will not refuſe to hearken to His great Councell, neither doth He challenge to Himſelfe any right of diſpoſing of your Lives, Lands and Liberties, but will protect you and them according to the eſtabliſhed Lawes: He only ſayes, He is not bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his own underſtanding, or to contradict His own conſcience for any Counſellors ſake whatſoever. He muſt ſatisfy that before their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, nor muſt that, which they call policy, give Law to that, which He knowes to be religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tis granted in things viſible, and certain, that judge which is a ſole judge, and has competent power to ſee his own judgement executed, ought not to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49803:34"/>againſt the light of nature, or evidence of fact.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Sole judge, or not, alters not the caſe, neither is there any reſtraint only to viſible and certain things; in the diſcharging of a truſt, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſt be guided by a morall certainty, or high probability.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſinne of</hi> Pilate <hi>was, that when he might have ſaved our Saviour from an unjuſt death, yet upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſations contradictory in themſelves; contrary to ſtrange revelations from Heaven, he would ſuffer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence to fall, and paſſe ſentence of death, meerly to ſatisfy a blood-thirſty multitude.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The ſinne of <hi>Pilate</hi> all confeſſe hainous, yet if examined according to his rule of juſtice, he muſt either condemne his own judgement, or abſolve his. For firſt, concerning ſtrange revelations to the contrary, all that I meet with is this, his wife ſent unto him, ſaying;
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.19</note> 
                  <hi>have thou nothing to doe with that juſt man, for I have ſuffered many things this day in a dream becauſe of him.</hi> What was revelation to her, was but a ſingle tradition to him, ſhe was obliged to beleeve God ſpeaking to her, he was not bound to believe a woman ſpeaking to him: he might think ſhe might be willing to deceive, out of naturall compaſſion ſtrong in that ſexe, or might be deceived her ſelfe, calling that inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49803:35"/>which was fancy. That it was true <hi>de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> makes nothing againſt him, for a Iudge, he knew, was to be guided by proofes, he that will paſſe ſentence according to what any ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have from Heaven, may well deſerve to goe to Hell for it.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Concerning accurations contradictory in themſelves, he ſaw that plainly and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes their teſtimonies invalid,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I find no fault in him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 27.18.</note> But it may be objected, <hi>he knew that for envy they had delivered him.</hi> That indeed was his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opinion, which the Iewes perſwade him was to be overruled by their authority, and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent. This therefore ſeems to be the caſe; <hi>Pilate</hi> thinks it not enough that all the chief Prieſts, and Elders of the people, cry out againſt him as a malefactor and enemy to the ſtate, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſome proofes, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.29. they returned this anſwer,
<note place="margin">v. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>if he were not a malefactor, we would not have delivered him unto thee, Populiſalus,</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth was in danger, not did it ſtand with the honour of that Aſſembly to give more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reaſons. At length he is reſolved to paſſe his aſſent, and yeelds to their votes upon theſe grounds:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His ſingle judgement was not to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49803:35"/>all advice; then many eyes of all the choyceſt of the people ſee more then his, and many ſpy faults which he could not find;</hi> beſides <hi>there was a Maxime and it was grounded upon nature</hi> (and which the Author ſaies was never 'till this Parliament withſtood, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then in full force) <hi>that a community can have no private ends to miſlead it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J ſhall only adde, the caſe can no way be vary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though they had not a joynt judiciall power, for if he thought him innocent, and knew he had ſuch a right, that except he paſſed ſentence againſt him he was not condemned, and ought not to ſuffer, it had been as high a fault to concurre with them in their injuſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not ſo; becauſe if one Iudge on the Bench diſſent from three, or one Iuror at the barre from eleven, they may ſubmit to the major number, though perhaps leſſe skilfull then themſelves, without imputation of guilt.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The Oath of the Iurors is this, as we find in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Lamberd, Se virum aliquem innocentem haud condemnaturos, ſonten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve abſoluturos.</hi> Laying their hands upon the holy Goſpell, every man ſwears, he will not condemne the innocent, nor abſolve the guilty. The words of their Oath now in uſe ſpeak the ſame ſenſe; They ſweare that they will doe right betwixt party and party, according to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49803:36"/>evidence given in: wherefore they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult information by witneſſes, not their fellowes votes. How his caſuiſts will ſatisfy a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when he violates this Oath, I know not. 'Tis true, in many caſes, there may be a legall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, but then the law doth not require a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall act contrary to conſcience, but provides for the preſervation of the innocency of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting parties, by making the act of the major part, have the force of the whole, according to that, <hi>Refertur ad vniverſos, quod publicè fit per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem partem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jf ſo in Law, much more in State, where the very ſatisfying a multitude, ſome times in things not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expedient, may prove not only expedient but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, for the ſetling of peace and ceaſing of strife.</hi>] True, if in Law, not otherwiſe: a Governour muſt not diſpleaſe God to pleaſe the people. The ſecond thing muſt be ordered according to the Rulers prudence. For many times, granting an unreaſonable requeſt, doth not ſatisfy, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their deſires. And whereas the more he gives, he becomes the leſſe able, ſo the more they receive, they become the more craving.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Militia and Magazine of</hi> Hull &amp;c. <hi>ſhould be intruſted into ſuch hands as were in the peoples good
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49803:36"/>eſteeme, conſcience and underſtanding could plead no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt it.</hi>] Underſtanding and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently conſcience very much, if the King had more diſtruſt of ſome, and more confidence in the fidelity of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it could have been averred (as it could not, for the contrary was true) that this would have bred di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, and have been the occaſion of greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>] Truly then he ſhall get the better, if he can impoſe upon our ſenſe, and make the Kingdom beleeve contrary to what they ſee, and ſuffer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. What hath been the cauſe of theſe unhappy diſtractions, but as the taking the Kings Towne from him by force, and the illegall alteration of the <hi>Militia,</hi> upon pretence of apparent danger? Though for a time, they were afraid, where no feare was, <hi>(quis illis ſic timere permiſit?)</hi> yet after they have had ſo long a time to recover their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and to conſider with themſelves, if the danger were apparent, it might in ſo many months be made evident, and they might know, whence to expect the blow, I dare now appeale to the weakeſt part of men their diſtruſts, and aske them, if they can now believe, there was any juſt ground for jealouſies. It is not improbable, ſince they have raiſed a houſe without a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49803:37"/>it may fall upon the heads of the maſter builders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where the people by publique authority will ſeek any inconvenience to themſelves, and the King is not ſo much intereſſed in it as themſelves, 'tis more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience and injustice to deny, then to grant it.</hi>]</p>
               <p>More injuſtice to deny then grant, therefore it ſeemes, that injuſtice too. Into what ſtreights muſt a King be brought by the mindes of the people! If they ſeek any inconvenience, injuſtice to deny it: O unheard of Maxims out of theſe new Politiques! that a King ſhould be bound by Law to deſtroy his people, and kill them out of duty; that he doth not preſerve their rights, except he doe them wrong. This <hi>affabile odium</hi> hath often had, but never deſerved thanks. Can a man imagine, thoſe people, of whom <hi>Juvenall</hi> ſpeaks,
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Evertêre domos totas optantibus ipſis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dii faciles,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> if they had underſtood their own prayers, would have accuſed the Gods for denying them? <hi>Charior eſt Regipopulus, quàm ſibi.</hi> How great are His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts towards His People, that will not ſuffer them to be miſerable, though they intreat him; though they provoke him to it; and can content
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49803:37"/>himſelfe with the conſcience of merit, whilſt his honour ſuffers under the envy of wrong doing! Indeed this is the end of all government; for the people finding they were not fit to govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, reſolved to be ruled by thoſe that were wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and ſo committed their ſafety to the truſt of others. Now this were to reduce themſelves to that firſt ſtate, which their ſufferings made them weary of, to place a Governour over them and to governe that Governour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What blame is it then in Princes, when they will pretend reluctance of conſcience and reaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No man juſtifies pretended conſcience, no man can condemne reall. But what grounds can ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice have to caſt this aſperſion of pretence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and reaſon? If we looke either on that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy miſunderſtanding of the people, who would not be undeceaved by pretences, his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt appeare unto them as cleare as the day; or on his owne neceſſities, his owne extreame wants, it cannot be. For certainly he that hath granted ſo much in this Parliament, and that in a ſhort time, as put all his Royall Anceſtors Acts of grace together, they fall much ſhort of his, would not have denyed any thing which was reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not any thing (ſince his wants required ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49803:38"/>from them) but what ſhould put him into farre worſe condition then that of Poverty.</p>
               <p>After a long and generall diſcourſe of the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of government, the various formes, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall diſtempers, whil'ſt policy was yet imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, he returnes to the preſent matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The vertue of Repreſentation hath been denyed to the Commons, and a ſeverance has been made betwixt the parties choſen, and the parties chooſing, and ſo that great priviledge of all priviledges, that unmoveable Baſis of all honour, and power, whereby the Houſe of Commons, claimes the entire right of all the Gentry and commonalty of England, has been attempted to be ſhaken and disturbed.</hi>]</p>
               <p>The ſenſe of it is, a truſt is committed to them, and they are to be guided according to conſcience in the performance of it. Let it be ſo: but is not this cleerly the Kings caſe, who is entruſted cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly as highly as they? So that they will find the ready way to endanger their own rights, is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon the Kings. Yet there may be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in the imputation of ſeverance and denyall of repreſentation to the Commons. For put the caſe; if a few men of a County preſent a Petition to the Houſe againſt eſtabliſhed lawes, and the ſetled Diſcipline of the Church; this is received,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49803:38"/>and thanks returned: if after, another Petition (modeſtly and diſcreetly expreſſing their deſires, and withall due reſpects to the Houſe, as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in that moſt excellent Petition of <hi>Kent</hi>) be preſented, atteſted by men much more eminent then the former, whether we reſpect number, Gentry, meanes or reputation; and this in favour of preſent government, which they have found happy by long experience, and therefore have no reaſon to be ſo deſirous of a change, of which they are not able to judge ſo well without tryall; this by no meanes is to be called a ſeverance or deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of repreſentation, though I confeſſe, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (apt to miſtake) may eaſily be deceived, and learn to miſcall it, becauſe the Gentlemen were impriſoned who preſented it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt of our late diſtempers and obſtructions in Parliaments have proceeded from this: that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon cauſeleſſe defamation, and unproved accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, have been ſo prone to withdraw themſelves from their repreſentatives, and yet there can be nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven, next to renouncing God, which can be more perfidious, and more pernitious in the people then this.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Here we may ſee the ſtrength of paſsion above reaſon. Certainly we never took the oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, nor of Allegiance unto them. Hence it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49803:39"/>will evidently follow, that Treaſon againſt a <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> is higher then that againſt the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This he grants as unqueſtionable, that <hi>the legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative power of this Kingdome, is partly in the King, and partly in the Kingdome, ſo that neither the King can make a generall binding Ordinance or Law, without the Parliament, or the Parliament without the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This one truth, if conſtantly ſtood to, would have prevented our miſeryes; and if yet embraced, might reſtore the Kingdome to happineſſe. But alas! it is ſoon recalled, as <hi>bolding only in ordinary caſes,</hi> but <hi>if the ſafety of the people be concerned, if it may prove dangerous, or inconvenient to them, then an extraordinary courſe may justly be taken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is it which hath ſo miſerably rent this Kingdome and cauſed theſe ſad diviſions. Firſt, the people are made beleeve they are in danger; and then a prevention of thoſe dangers is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: This muſt needs be very gratefull to them, ſo out of that naturall love they bear to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they favour that ſide, which pretends to take care of their ſafety. His way of arguing is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plauſible, and ſeemeth to carry more ſtrength, becauſe it worketh upon our underſtanding by our affection. The ſumme is this; in caſe of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and imminent danger the Peoples ſafety
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49803:39"/>is not to be neglected; they ought not to be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a Prey to the enemy, who if he take them unprovided will deſtroy them all, therefore moſt fit they ſhould be put into a poſture of defence: now none ſo fit Iudges of this apparent and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger, as the two Houſes; wherefore they to order this <hi>Militia.</hi> So that it muſt be in their power, to command Men, raiſe Horſes, ſeize on all the Ammunition, ſend for what ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of mony they think neceſſary for repelling theſe dangers, elſe they are not ſufficiently enabled for that great work, the peoples preſervation. Here we are falne back again into (what we ſo much complained of). Arbitrary power, nor is the thing taken away, but placed in another body; all that we have gained is only this, we ſhall not be beaten by the ſame hand. Was not this the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſe of Ship-mony? upon ſuppoſall of a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and the Kingdom being in danger, very fit to ſecure it and the people; this cannot be done without money, the danger will not allow the delay of asking the Subjects conſent, and going the ordinary way of Law, therefore an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe them becomes legall, and very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable it is, the Subject ſhould be content to part with ſome, rather then looſe all now who fitter
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49803:40"/>to judge of this neceſsity then the King, as being moſt fully informed by His advantage of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from His Embaſſadors, Agents &amp;c. of the deſignes of forraigne Princes and States.</p>
               <p>To wind our ſelves out of this Labyrinth, we will goe on thoſe grounds, on which they argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Ship-mony, for as the Argument runnes parallell, ſo will the anſwer. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was laid downe as a ſure ground of reaſon, that it was better for the Kingdom, though it were in reall danger, <hi>in arenâ conſilium capere,</hi> to ſhift for it ſelfe, as well as it was able, by a ſuddain defence, then that the Law ſhould provide ſuch a remedy, which would be ſo eaſily, ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed upon every pretence of danger, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch an evill, which could extreamly ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or almoſt never happen, for an Army and Navy could not be ſo ſecretly provided, but that we muſt have ſome intelligence of it. So in the caſe of the <hi>Militia,</hi> it is much better, that by being continued in the old legall way, it ſhould hazard it ſelfe to ſuch a poſsible danger, then that Law ſhould provide ſuch a remedy (for what proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly will never happen) as being abuſed upon pretences, may every three years put the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in combuſtion. To repell danger any way
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49803:40"/>but by Law, is the greateſt danger of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let the world judge, whether the pronouncing</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Iohn Hotham's <hi>act: Treaſon be not contrary to the cleareſt beams of humane reaſon, and the ſtrongeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of nature: for every private man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelfe by force, if aſſaulted, though by the force of a Magiſtrate, or his own father, and though he be not without all confidence by flight.</hi>]</p>
               <p>He is ſtrongly reſolved upon the concluſion, that will bring it in upon ſuch premiſes. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>John Hotham</hi> his aſſeizing on the Kings Towne and Ammunition was it ſeemes in his own defence; who aſſaulted him? did His Majeſty drive him into <hi>Hull?</hi> what can he think of the Gunpowder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traitors, was their reſiſtance a juſt defence? then certainly every Rebellion is a juſt warre. Indeed what is that thing which we call obedience, if a man may refuſe to ſubmit to Law in his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here whole Nations being expoſed to enmity and hazard, being utterly uncapable of flight, muſt yeeld their throats and ſubmit to aſſaſsinates, if their King will not allow them defence.</hi>] There is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a Subjects defending himſelfe, and offending his King. His fears are over-witty, if they will not permit him to think himſelfe ſafe,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49803:41"/>except he get into one of the Kings ſorts for his better ſecurity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See if we are not left as a prey to the ſame bloody hands, as have done ſuch diabolicall exploits in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>&amp;c. if we may not take up armes for our own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or if it be poſsible for us to take up armes, without ſome Votes, or Ordinances to regulate the</hi> Militia.] Subjects upon in vaſion would not have wanted Commiſſion to take up armes; till then they are ſafe enough by the benefit of the Law, which could not poſsibly have better provided for their ſafety, then by denying them a power to take armes as often as ambitious: choletick men for their own ends ſhall perſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them they are it danger. For by this meanes, being eaſily deceived, whileſt they endeavoured to avoyd falſe, they would run themſelves headlong into true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King ſaies; the Parliament denies &amp;c. to whether now in this uncertainty, is the Subject bound to adhere?</hi>]</p>
               <p>It is poſsible, circumſtances may afford us ſome light for our direction. We may conſider, whether the Houſes doe not barely ſay; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther His Majeſty doth not deſcend ſo farre, as to give reaſons for what He does; and to ſhew the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49803:41"/>Kingdom the ground of His actions, by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar citation of the Lawes, which juſtify them. We ought to agree whether ſwerving from Law, be to be judged by the action, or by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that is, if the King ſhould have done; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they did, and the Houſes what ever He did, whether all would not then have been legall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe done by them. The King doth not deſire to captivate any mans underſtanding to His au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but is willing to make all the world the judge of His actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither is a blind obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a part of any mans duty to the Houſes. The beſt way to diſcerne a right, will be to conſult the rule, which is Law, and not meaſure the legality of an act by the doer. Some things are matters of fact, here we may be guided by ſenſe, and judge as we ſee. As whether the King has ſeized on any thing, wherein the Subject hath a property? or whether the Subject hath not ſeized upon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wherein the King hath a property? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King hath raiſed warre againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that is, whether His Guard was an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and whether <hi>Hull</hi> is now <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We had a maxime and it was grounded upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and never till this Parliament withſtood, that a community can have no private ends to miſlead it,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49803:42"/>and make it injurious to it ſelfe.</hi>]</p>
               <p>True in a ſtate where the collective body aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles: and the reaſon of it is evident; for though every man aime at his greateſt particular intereſt, yet except it be agreeable to the intereſt of the major part it will never paſſe into an Act; and if it be advantageous for the moſt, it is to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med publique. Now what ſervice this can doe the two Houſes, I cannot ſee, becauſe they are a repreſentative body. If he pleaſe to conſult <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> or <hi>Tacitus,</hi> he may find what moſt unworthy ends the <hi>Senate</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> propoſed to themſelves, and be quickly ſatisfied in the falſehood of this Maxime, taken in his ſenſe. The truth is he raiſes probabilities into demonſtrations, and becauſe it is not ſo likely, (it being a work of greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty) that four hundred ſhould contrive things for their private intereſts, as that four ſhould, the takes it for impoſſible. Whereas experience clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confutes him; in other ſtates we find nothing more common. That we in <hi>England</hi> have ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſuffered under ſuch corruptions, proceeds from cauſes which are peculiar to this govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It was a court for the moſt part, but of ſhort continuance, ſo that they had not time to mould and faſhion their aimes; and when called
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49803:42"/>together againe, the body was much altered. But the chief reaſon, and that to which the Subject eſpecially owes his ſecurity, is this, that the finall determination, is not in one, nor two houſes, but the joynt conſent of three Eſtates is neceſſary. So that nothing is likely to paſſe, but what is for the intereſt of the major part, and what is ſo, is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely advantagious. It is more poſſible they may now proſequute private intereſts, ſince they challenge a power to themſelves ſufficient to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their deſignes; which heretofore they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pretending to, could not hope to compaſſe particular ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King may ſafely leave His higheſt rights to Parliaments.</hi>] If this be all the motive, he may as ſafely keep them. Why did the Lawes entruſt Him with them, if it were fitting for Him to make no uſe of them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>None knows better, or affects more the ſweetneſſe of this ſo well ballanced a Monarchy.</hi>] I believe they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Monarchy, why then doth this Author en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take it away, by denying the King a power of diſſent, which our Anceſtors inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſerved, as a moſt happy reſtraint of Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy or Democracy?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It hath been often in the power of former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49803:43"/>to load that rule with greater fetters and cloggs, but they would not.</hi>] A very good argument, there is little reaſon now to doe it. After a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the exact temper and due proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the three Eſtates, the many affecting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy better then Ariſtocracy, and the Nobility preferring it as much beyond Democracy.</p>
               <p>He exhorts us <hi>not to ſeek to corrupt this purity of compoſition.</hi>] Very good counſell: but which he overthrowes in the words immediatly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>We must not conceive, that both Gentry and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility can combine againſt the King.</hi> Therefore it will be fitting for the King to leave all to their diſpoſall, who certainly can doe nothing, but what is fitting. In how few words hath he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that conſtitution, which he told us was ſo perfect, it could admit of no change but for worſe? But we could not ſtay here, if the Kings negative were once taken away, like decaying bodies, our health would dayly impaire. The next ſtep muſt be, the Lords ſitting in a perſonall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, no reaſon they ſhould deny what the Kingdom hath voted to be neceſſary or conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; either let them not ſpeak at all, or let the greater part of Commons joyne with the leſſer part of Peeres.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49803:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The right of all the Lords and Commons in this State is ſo great, that no change of government can be advantage to them, except they could each one attain an hereditary Crowne.</hi>] May they not attain as much as Malignant Counſellors are pretended to aime at, Honours, Offices, Wealth, Power, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their power is meerly derivative, ſo that except we will conceive that both King and People will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the uſurpation, nothing can be done.</hi>] Then it is confeſt, the King hath a right of diſſenting. <hi>Except both King and People;</hi> here a power is given to the People collectively, beyond the Lords, Commons and King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the King be an affector of true Liberty, He has in Parliament a Power as extenſive as ever the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Dictators was for the preventing of publike di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes.</hi>] The Dictator had abſolute Authority; nor was he circumſcribed in power, but in time on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. There lay no appeale from him, neither was he queſtionable for any action after his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment expired. Though the humor of that people could not endure the name of King, they had the ſame thing; for in imminent dangers, whether from forrain invaſions, or inteſtine ſeditions, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſtate forced them to ſubmit to his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49803:44"/>which relieved them in their greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities.</p>
               <p>Hence we may make the trueſt judgement, what forme of government the wiſeſt Romans eſteemed moſt convenient, their actions, which proceeded from feare, were unfeigned interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their thoughts. That they fell back ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their old rule, and were not as wiſe to prevent dangers by conſerving that Authority, as they were to encounter them by erecting it, muſt be imputed to the inconſtant temper of the people, who in times of peace were as proud and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, as when ruine threatned (which their wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe pulled upon themſelves) they were baſely humble: Since then the Romans preferred even the unbounded power of one to a popular ſway, wee have no reaſon to change the much more happy temper of this government, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Monarchy is ſo wiſely ballanced, that as we are not expoſed to the dangers which attend the rule of the many, ſo we may avoyd the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which might probably flow from the Arbitrary power of one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He hath met in the field with two contrary Armies of His own Subjects, and yet that Army, which He went to destroy, and advanced their colours againſt Him,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49803:44"/>was more loyall then that which himſelfe commanded.</hi>] Had he made a Conſcience of unjuſt ſlander, or had he any ſenſe of the honour of his Nation, theſe words had never fowled the paper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which the King here calls conſcience and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, can be nothing elſe but meer private opinion.</hi>] What other poſsible notion can any man have of conſcience? is it not the light of reaſon infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming us in our duty? <hi>If the Counſell of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament were directly oppoſite to common underſtanding and good conſcience, and the Counſell of the Court were evidently conſonant thereunto, there needed no ſuch conteſtation.</hi>] If the Counſell of the Court were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to common underſtanding and good conſcience, and the Counſell of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were evidently conſonant thereunto, there would be no ſuch conteſtation.</p>
               <p>It is a very unfaithfull way of judging, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the goodneſſe of Counſell by the perſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing, not by the thing adviſed. His Majeſty all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes examined what, not who, and hath given His Subjects a moſt certain pledge of His Royall affection, in paſsing ſo many good Acts, and was reſolved to grant, as long as any thing could in reaſon be deſired. After He hath fully ſatisfied the publique intereſt, even to the utmoſt extent, of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49803:45"/>what moſt underſtanding and disingaged men wiſh for, he is not bound to undoe again in part, and ſo farre to comply with the intereſts of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men, as to place a power in ſome, by which they ſhall be able to hinder His good people from enjoying the full benefits of His Royall Grace, if ſuch a conſent appear to Him to doe it.</p>
               <p>The following diſcourſe keeps all in generalls (which eaſily deceive weaker apprehenſions) and hath its ſtrength from this ground, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reaſonably be ſuppoſed the great &amp; publique Councell of the Kingdome ſhould not give the moſt faithfull advice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Princes, if they may not be led by their owne opinions, rather then by the ſacred and awfull Councells of whole Nations, unreaſonably complain they are denyed liberty of Conſcience, and raviſht out of their own underſtandings.</hi>] I appeal to any mans judgment, whether any thing can be urged for the authority of a Lay-Councell, that it ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force a ſubmiſſion of judgment, &amp; a performance of dutyes ariſing from truſt agreeable thereto, which may not with at leaſt equall advantages, be preſſed for the ſame binding power in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells Eccleſiaſticall. To inſtance in that of <hi>Trent,</hi> if a Papiſt ſhould, (as <hi>Campian</hi> doth) bragg of that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49803:45"/>to him as the repreſentative body of almoſt all the Weſtern Church, wherein was a concourſe of ſo many choiſe, able, eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, ſuch as had addicted their whole times to the ſtudy of truth, and therefore in all probability could not be deceived themſelves, &amp; ſuch as had converſed ſo long with Heaven and Heavenly things, they knew ſufficiently how much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned them not to deceive others, and conclude it therefore unlawfull for any to pretend conſcience (which is but private opinion) againſt ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and unanimous determination. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe high probabilities, and (what will much more juſtify mens abſolute obedience, and captivating their reaſons, ſome plauſible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for a divine aſsiſtance, and immediate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in all their deciſions, which the Houſes will not pretend to;) yet it ſhall goe hard but he will find ſome anſwer (as eſily he might) whereby to juſtifie his liberty of diſſenting in ſome things, which when he hath done, he may with very little alteration apply to civill Councells and be ſatisfied. Suppoſe it thus: though amongſt probable Arguments, that drawn from authority of wiſe men carry with it greateſt weight, yet it muſt give place to a greater
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49803:46"/>reaſon. Now to every man belongs a judgment of diſcretion, which muſt decide for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes his particular duty. So in the Kings caſe: the Votes which carry in them the authority of both Houſes, ſhall bear great ſway, and if it be in things extreamly dubious, they may turn the ſcales of their ſide. But if greater reaſon ſeem to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them, his Majeſty will not hoodwink His underſtanding, and blindly follow whither they pleaſe to lead him, He will walke by the greater Light; For example his Majeſty perceiving how much His people may ſuffer under arbitrary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is reſolved never to make uſe of it, &amp; thinks it leſſe fitting any other ſhould. But it is told him now the uſe of it will be for their good, by reaſon of apparent imminent dangers. His Majeſty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the bottome of plauſible pretences, &amp; knows to how great miſchiefes a way would be opened, if it were ſufficient upon ſuch ſpecious grounds to have a right to over-rule all known and certain Lawes.</p>
               <p>Concerning the action at <hi>Hull,</hi> he confeſſes, <hi>to take poſſeſsion of the Kings town and ſhut the gates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him is Treaſon, if circumſtances doe not vary the nature of the act, as in this Caſe he pretends they doe. For the first thing to be lookt on is, that the King
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49803:46"/>was meerly denyed entrance for that time, His generall right was not denyed.</hi>] If then a Subject take up Armes againſt his Soveraign in a temporary warr, it muſt not come within the compaſſe of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and he may legally poſſeſſe himſelfe of the King's forts, and maintaine them againſt Him, ſo He confeſſe he hath no right in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No defying language was given.</hi> If a man take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my purſe, ſhall he be acquitted from felony becauſe he did not give me ill language too? <hi>No act of violence was uſed.</hi> This he may ſay who hath pickt anothers pocket; but it is no ſufficient plea againſt the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But he uſed no violence, though the King for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe houres together did ſtand within Musket ſhot, &amp;c:</hi>] It is no argument of innocence that he had opportunity to be more highly guilty, and abſtained.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King uſed tearmes of defiance, and this makes the act meerly defenſive, or rather paſsive.</hi>] If this were true, there was never any warr but defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; for thoſe, who by ſome great injuſtice offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, provoke a Nation to right it ſelf, fight as well to maintain their lives, as what they unlawfully poſſeſſe. <hi>How this ſhould adminiſter to the King any ground to leavy guards at</hi> York, <hi>many men wonder,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49803:47"/>or that it ſhould ſeem the ſame thing to the King, as if He had been purſued to the gates of</hi> York.]</p>
               <p>Certainly it was a ſufficient ground, not only to raiſe a guard for His ſafety, but an Army to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that high indignity, and right His Honour: but out of tender care of His Peoples ſafety (leaſt they ſhould chance to ſuffer upon miſtakes) He afforded him ſo long time of repentance, that the Kingdome might firſt be ſatisfyed, and then his juſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the Parliament have hereupon turned any of the Townes-men out of their Eſtates.</hi> His Majeſty did not charge the two Houſes; Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> kept Him out, without any publike order from them. But if it had been done <hi>de facto,</hi> the ſame law would have juſtified this act, as well as the other. But ſince, not only the Country about, but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants within the Town have ſuffered in their Eſtates, and libertyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or if claimed any intereſt in it to themſelves.</hi> So much the leſſe reaſon to ſeize on it, if he cannot ſo much as pretend title to it. <hi>or have diſſeized the King, utterly denying the right for the future.</hi> If any Law can be produced to juſtifie taking away the Kings goods for a time, the caſe will be cleered. <hi>Or have made any other uſe of their poſſeſsion but
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49803:47"/>meerly to prevent civill warr.</hi> There is not any way more likely to create a Civill warr, then endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prevent it by illegall courſes. <hi>And to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſh the King's ſeducers of Armes &amp; Ammunition: therefore the most eſſentiall property of Treaſon, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, muſt needs here be abſent in this act.</hi>] The Law hath judged otherwiſe in the caſe of the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> whoſe plea was, he intended the removall of evill Counſellors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the Parliament</hi> (the ſhutting the King out of <hi>Hull</hi> was not their act) <hi>be not vertually the whole Kingdome it ſelfe.</hi> The King excluded it is not; <hi>If it be not the Supream judicature, as well in matters of State, as matters of Law.</hi> Till new lawes are ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, the Subject cannot juſtify any act, but what is warrantable by the old. <hi>If it be not the great Councell of the Kingdome as well as of the King, to whom it belongeth by the conſent of all Nations to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide in all extraordinary caſes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e quid detriment capiat Reſpublica, <hi>let the brand of Treaſon ſtick upon it.</hi> No proviſions are allowed, but what are legall leaſt the Remedy ſhould prove the greateſt diſeaſe. <hi>Nay if the Parliament would have uſed this forcible meanes unleſſe petitioning would not have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed.</hi> It is no juſt excuſe to take away a mans money, and ſay he did firſt deſire him to deliver it.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49803:48"/>
                  <hi>Or if their grounds of jealouſy were meerly vaine.</hi> It is againſt all equity to doe wrong, becauſe there is a poſſibility of ſuffering it; no man can have a full ſecurity; and therefore we muſt arme our ſelves againſt uncertain feares, not by injuries, but a wary innocence. <hi>Or if the jealouſy of a whole Kingdom can be counted vaine.</hi>] Too large an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion; much the greater part of the Kingdom apprehend no juſt grounds of jealouſies.</p>
               <p>Though the mindes of many were a long time unſetled, being daily diſturbed by ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons of plots at home, and invaſions from abroad, yet if we duly weigh the buſineſſe, ſuch fears ought not to be valued. If forty ſeverall men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte the ſame thing, yet if upon examination thirty nine of them ſay they had it from the other man, this in Law makes but one witneſſe; ſo the fears of many thouſands, if grounded upon infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and thoſe informations come from ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, who can no way evidence the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſuch reports, they ought not to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they will vaniſh into nothing. <hi>Or if they claime any ſuch right of judging of dangers and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting them without the King's conſent as ordinary and perpetuall.</hi> As often as they have a mind to make uſe of ſuch a right, 'tis eaſy for them to call
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49803:48"/>the caſe extraordinary, and pretend a publike danger. For my part I know not how they can ever be confuted, if not now. For certainly appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent dangers did never leſſe appeare. It would more abundantly have ſatisfied me, if I had been frighted with ſecret plots, and conceald de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King might have prevented the ſame repulſe by ſending a meſſenger before hand.</hi> That is, if He had not come to get in, He had not been ſhut out; if He would have ſtayed away, he would not have denyed Him entrance. <hi>Or by coming without any ſuch conſiderable forces.</hi> Let His forces be great, he was not to give Law to his Prince. but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it likely he would have admitted Him then, for you confeſſe a little above, <hi>He offered to enter</hi> Hull <hi>with twenty horſe only, unarmed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Scots <hi>in</hi> England <hi>took</hi> New-caſtle <hi>but by private authority, yet there were other qualifications in that act ſufficient to purge it of Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King and Parliament deſerved ſo much reſpect from you, as not to have inſtanced ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in their Act; you might well let that paſſe in ſilence, which they have buried in an Act of oblivion.</p>
               <p>He flouriſhes at large upon the <hi>example of</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:49803:49"/>Richard <hi>the ſecond</hi> (he means <hi>Edw.</hi> 2.) <hi>miſled by</hi> Spencer. It doth not follow, becauſe one King hearkned to evill counſell, therefore all muſt be denied the liberty to hearken to good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spencer's party was but of inconſiderable fortunes.</hi> He will get no advantage by putting mens eſtates into the Scales, and ballancing their reputations. At length yet there is ſome little hopes he may prove a convert, ſince he doth almoſt promiſe to ſuſpend his judgement, till he may have full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction from His Majeſties Narration, which in due time will more fully informe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Aristocracy in Parliament cannot be erected withoutſome means, and what this means ſhall be, is yet to us altogether inſcrutable.</hi> Certainly he is quicker ſighted then not to perceive what is ſo obvious. Deny the King a negative, and the thing is done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The power of Parliaments is but derivative and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon publique conſent, and how publique con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhould be gained for the erection of a new unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full odious Tyranny amongſt us, is not diſcernable.</hi>] It is not thought this was the intent of thoſe that entruſted them, but it may be the abuſe of power, if the Kings authority be once ſwallowed up in theirs. For though their power depend upon a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49803:49"/>publique conſent in the election, yet not ſo after they are met together. The neceſſities of the time made His Majeſty grant, that this Parliament ſhould not be diſſolved without their conſent; but they may now challenge it as their right, if the King be bound to confirme, what they vote neceſſary or expedient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it cannot be: and his reaſon is, the Kingdom would not obey them.</hi>] In truth a very probable thing: I beleeve they would not be able to goe through in that new way. But yet they muſt needs have a great party; conſidering their ſeverall rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the advantage they have, in advancing the intereſts, whether religious or civill, of ſome, which may be able to doe them ſervice, and this would create diviſion in the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty expreſſes His juſt indignation, that they (He imputes it not to the Houſes, though this Author ſtill involve them, but to the contrivers &amp; penners of the Declaration) ſhould dare to tell their King, <hi>they may without want of modeſty or duty depoſe him:</hi> He returnes anſwer, <hi>this cannot be collected from thoſe words,</hi> That if they ſhould make the higheſt preſidents of other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments their patterne, there would be no cauſe to complain of want of modeſty and duty, <hi>becauſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49803:50"/>it may juſtly be denied that free Parliaments did ever truly conſent to the dethroning of any King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> What was there affirmed of Parliaments had none of his preſent reſtriction of Free in it. If the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. Were indeed not Free, why were Statutes cited out of it? The authors of thoſe quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations muſt be preſumed to accompt it ſo.</p>
               <p>The King is offended at their franck expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſguiſed under the charge of a malignant party. The ſenſe of his anſwer is this, they have no other way to cleere themſelves: for there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faults ſomewhere, not to lay them upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, were to take them upon themſelves. His Majeſty hath propoſed a very good way which will fully ſatisfy the world in their innocency, and that is not alwaies to accuſe, but ſometimes to prove.</p>
               <p>The King demands juſtice for tumults and high indignities offered, and complaines of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition ſent from the Houſe of Commons into <hi>Southwarke,</hi> to hinder the proceſſe againſt a Riot according to Law. His anſwer is, <hi>equall juſtice could not be obtained againſt the Court-Cavaleeres.</hi> His Majeſty never protected them from legall tryall; it was free for them to have proved what they could againſt them.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49803:50"/>
               <p>The Kingſaies, it being granted by them, that their priviledges doe not extend to Treaſon, Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or breach of the Peace, ſo as to exempt the Members from all manner of tryall, yet if they be ſo priviledged in the method of their tryall, that the cauſe muſt firſt be brough before them, and their conſent asked before you can proceed, then their Priviledges extend as farre in theſe, as in the moſt unqueſtioned caſes; becauſe no priviledge exempts them from all manner of tryall, the Houſe being acquainted and leave given, He ſayes nothing can take of this: it was fully inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Members ſhould have had a legall and ſpeedy tryall; for His Majeſty conceives it high injuſtice to clap men up upon a bare charge, and after they are in priſon, forget there are ſuch men in the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Parliament does not deny the King a true reall intereſt in anything held by him, either in</hi> jure Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, <hi>or in</hi> jure Perſonae, <hi>but only affirmes that in the ſame thing the State hath an intereſt</hi> Paramont <hi>in caſes of publique extremity; by vertue of which it may justly ſeize and uſe the ſame for its own neceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</hi>] The King is a part of the ſtate, and therefore the other part hath not any power war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Law, to doe what they think fit to His
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49803:51"/>prejudice, upon pretence of publique extremity. This is ſhip-money again; in every mans lands &amp; goods, the State hath an intereſt <hi>Paramount</hi> in caſes of publique extremity, by vertue of which it may juſtly ſeize, and uſe the ſame for its own ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary preſervation. Heres the difference, the head without the body was the State before; now it is the body without a head. The King hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly freed us from that inconvenience, and we hope He will not ſuffer us to be oppreſt with this. The prudence of our lawes hath provided againſt either; but were there a neceſſity we muſt fall into one, we ought in reaſon to chooſe the former, we are acquainted with that, and therefore could better digeſt it: It would be a great affliction to fall from ſuch hopes, and what we lookt on as a remedy, to find that our diſeaſe: but eſpecially it would be leſſe burthen to our eſtates, to ſatisfy one, then five hundred.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the King's things are still reſerved for him in better hands, then he would have put them.</hi> Though this were true it were an ill preſident for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, who muſt be bound to give up his meanes as oft as they conceive they could diſpoſe it more wiſely, as they yet keep them away from him for his good, ſo hereafter they may ſpend them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49803:51"/>him for his advantage. Let what will be pretended; the Subject cannot be ſo ſtupid, as not to underſtand, theſe, who undertake to manage the <hi>Paramount</hi> intereſt of the State, may ſeize on any ſubjects fortunes, by the ſame right they take the King's.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That there is an Arbitrary power in every State ſomewhere, 'tis true, 'tis neceſſary, and no inconvenience followes upon it.</hi>] If he mean by arbitrary, a legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power, this is granted, yet not to a part, but the whole body. But this ſpeakes not to the caſe; for ſtill they give us a certain rule to live by. The old lawes are in force, till repealed, and when new are once enacted, we muſt conform our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to thoſe ſtanding rules. He is to juſtifie, there is ſuch a <hi>Paramount</hi> Law, which ſhall make all our other lawes truly Oracles, that is, capable of contrary meanings. So that now a man may be juſtly puniſht for doing ſuch a thing, becauſe he hath diſobeyed the letter of the law; a week af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſhall be juſtly puniſht too, for not doing the ſame thing, becauſe he hath diſobeyed the equity of the Law. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us (and 'tis very wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Rhet. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. Thoſe lawes are
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49803:52"/>with greateſt prudence eſtabliſhed, which define moſt caſes, and leave nothing, which poſsibly may be determined, to the breſt of the judge. The reaſon of it is this; Lawes are made without any reſpects to perſons, it cannot be foreſeen what parties would be engaged; but Judges doe not all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abſtract from theſe; they may be miſlead by the relation of Kinſman, friend, Patron, or other intereſts. Now how fully may theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ends be ſatisfied by this equitable conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Law?</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hooker <hi>does not ſay, that the Anabaptiſts in</hi> Germany <hi>did deceive Parliaments with their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſye.</hi>] No man told you he did; we only learne thus much from that ſtory of their foul injuſtice and cruelty, that upon proportionable principles, ſuch miſchiefes being then, may be again. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if a power be placed in a certain body of men, by which they are allowed to breake all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour lawes, if they think it is for the good of the people, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> and if this body be backt by the greater part of the people, as having gained on their affections by fair promiſes of a perfect refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and that they ſhall at length enjoy the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſimplicity of the Goſpell; in this caſe may it not be a ſufficient motive to take away mens
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49803:52"/>eſtates, becauſe they cannot confide in them? is it not juſt to take from enemies of the State the power of hurting it? 'Tis very obvious, that for thoſe men, of whom they have no good opinion to have wealth may be a crime, to have honours treaſonable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for the thirty Tyrants of</hi> Athens, <hi>we know they were not choſen by the people, as our Knights, Citizens, &amp;c:</hi> This circumſtance alters not the caſe, if after they are elected, they challenge as unqueſtionable and as irrevocable power. But the main intent of that inſtance was, to ſhew there may be a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of many, and that much more miſerable then that of one, in many reſpects. If the inordinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of one are hardly ſatisfied, how much more may we ſuffer under thoſe of many? we cannot hope to weary them. If we muſt be ſlaves, better to have one maſter, then foure hundred. Though the blowes were equall, that from a Royall hand would not ſmart ſo much; it wounds the very ſoul to be trampled on by equalls. The weight of preſent evills would leſſe afflict, then the fear of future. There may be continuall ſupply of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; new and hungry flyes may ſucceed in the room of the old, and ſuck ſtrongly, not regarding many have already been glutted. Neither can we
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49803:53"/>expect an end of theſe miſeries, ſuch a body is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, whereas the vices of a Prince are perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and dye with the man, we may be reſtored to happineſſe by His ſucceſſor.</p>
               <p>I will in briefe relate the ſtory of their reigne. They had got into their hands the power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring what was Law, and this by the conſent of the people. In the beginning they call ſome men into Queſtion, who were much hated by the Citty; and though the law could not take hold of them ſo farre, yet they paſt ſentence of death. This was very plauſible to moſt, who judged of this proceeding by the rule of their preſent affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, not looking ſo farre into the future, as to conſider, what ill conſequences this might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; for by the ſame way innocent men might be cut off, if they were pleas'd to call them enemies of the State. After this they gave ſome part of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique authority to three thouſand of the Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and diſarmed all the reſt, by this means (and the benefit of a <hi>Militia</hi> from <hi>Sparta</hi>) the Citty was wholly in their diſpoſall. In a ſhort time they had committed ſo many outrages, and ſuch high injuſtice, that <hi>Theramenes,</hi> one of their own body, one of the thirty, profeſſed his publique diſlike of thoſe proceedings. Then was he accuſed as a
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49803:53"/>Traitor to them, and (though it was a priviledge of the three thouſand, that none of them ſhould ſuffer death by the ſentence of the thirty, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to accuſtomed proceſſe and tryall) yet <hi>Critias</hi> wip't his name out of that number, and ſo reduced him to their tryall. <hi>Theramenes</hi> pleads for himſelfe; they ought to look upon his as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon caſe; their names might as eaſily be blotted out, he adviſes them to be very wary in making ſuch a preſident which might ruine them and their poſterity. The iſſue was this: Particular men being over-awed by their fears, thought it their wiſeſt way to hold their peace, ſince if they ſhould ſpeak in his behalfe, there was little hopes to redeeme him, but great probability to ruine themſelves. So they choſe rather to expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thoſe future inconveniences, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly might not come upon them, then hazard a preſent danger. By this advantage the Tyrants prevailed and condemned him to dye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The things taken from the King at</hi> Hull <hi>were Armes, which are of more danger then other kind of chattels.</hi>] By the ſame Law all that part of the Kingdom which is not confided in may be diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nay why may not their mony be taken too, upon probable feare they may buy armes with it?
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49803:54"/>The Subject is in a miſerable condition that is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be undone as often as they pleaſe to be fearfull. It is ſo farre from excuſing, it aggravates the fact, to take away the Kings Armes, that is the meanes whereby he may ſeize what ever elſe belongs unto His Majeſty. The Law of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath only intruſted the Prince with Armes, ſo, that the Subject ought not to be arraied, trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and muſtered, but by His Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſome determination muſt be ſupream, and therefore either the Kings power and truſt muſt be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the diſcretion of the Parliament, or elſe the Parliament and all other Courts must be overruled by the Kings meer diſcretion.</hi>] No neceſſity of either; For in caſes of this nature, which he confeſſes to be extraordinary, if the King and Parliament diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, things muſt be at a ſtand, and the Subject muſt be obedient to the ordinary Law. The caſe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as it is laid down by His Majeſty, is unanſwerable, and therefore he is forced to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ſhifts, being unable to ſay any thing materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and yet unwilling to hold his peace.</p>
               <p>England <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>are one and the ſame Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, there is as true and intimate an union betwixt them, as betwixt</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales.] If this were ſo, <hi>Iriſh</hi> Barons would be <hi>Engliſh</hi> Peeres, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49803:54"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> Peeres would have a right to vote in <hi>Iriſh</hi> Parliaments. Beſides all lawes here enacted would ſtand in full force in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they doe in the Kings dominion of <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though the major part ſhould vote a thing, yet if it be diſliked here, they would want authority to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the thing ſo voted. For the reaſon why the minor part in all ſuffrages ſubſcribes to the major, is, that blood may not be ſhed, for in probability the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part will prevaile.</hi> This is a good reaſon for ſuch a contract, that the minor part ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; but after ſuch agreement in States, juſtice laies an obligation on them ſo to doe: upon his grounds, if the leſſer part in Parliament though never ſo few, can make it appeare the greater part of the Kingdom are of their opinion, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part ought to ſubſcribe to the minor. Nay, if at any time the major part of <hi>Ireland</hi> joyning with the minor part of <hi>England,</hi> make a major of the whole, then the major part in our Parliament muſt ſit downe. He takes no notice of the other caſe: ſuppoſe the malignant party ſhould be a major part of both Houſes, which His Majeſty ſhewes how very probably it might have been, and were there a new election, it is not impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Counties ſhould ſend up the greater
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49803:55"/>part of ſuch men as he calls malignant, would he think the King bound to conſent to all ſuch alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as they ſhould propoſe?</p>
               <p>Some ſcattering reaſons are laid down con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> which are but repetitions of what I have formerly anſwered.</p>
               <p>A Faction is ſaid to have prevailed upon a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part, by cunning, force, abſence, or accident. He argues thus againſt it; <hi>if by cunning, we muſt ſuppoſe the King's party in Parliament, has loſt all their Law policy and ſubtilty.</hi>] The reaſon why they are over-borne, may be this; not becauſe they have leſſe Law, but more Honeſty, which will not permit them to maintain a good cauſe by ill meanes. We all know in how great ſtead thoſe <hi>piae fraudes, holy falſhoods, and religious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths</hi> ſtood the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though there were ſuch who laid down better reaſons for the contrary opinions, yet truth prevailed ſlowly and with a few only, becauſe the minds of moſt were craftily prepoſſeſt with prejudice againſt it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and nouriſhed by fained ſtories. The diſpute proceeded upon very unequall termes; for the Roman party gave themſelves the liberty of taking all advantages, whereas their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were forced to betray a good cauſe out of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49803:55"/>meer ingenuity: they had none of their ſide who could lye. We ought to examine, whether this policy work not (at leaſt in the beginning, till a diſcovery of their falſhoods is made, and the people is undeceived) the ſame effects in a civill State; whether there are not ſuch things, as <hi>fraudes</hi> (pretended to be) <hi>reipublicae ſalutares,</hi> which have ſo ſtrong an influence on the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings of many, that they can ſubmit to the votes of ſome, who have inſinuated themſelves into their affections, againſt the cleer reaſons of others, whom they have been taught cauſeleſly to ſuſpect. How eaſy is it to deceive by giving in falſe informations of dangers from abroad? If ſome, more ſcrupulous then to be abuſed and led away by light reports, inquire after the hand that they may judge of the probability of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, according to the faith and credit of the relator, they muſt be ſatisfied with this, the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer deſires his name ſhould be concealed, <hi>Pour l'eviter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le tiltre d'eſpion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It cannot be by force, becauſe they have no army viſible.</hi>] A thing is ſaid in Law to be done by force, not only when men actually ſuffer, if they make uſe of their liberty, and refuſe to ſatisfy the paſsion and humor of ſome, but then alſo when
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49803:56"/>they have juſt grounds of feare, for this works on the mind, as ſtrongly as the other on the body. And therefore <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us, ſtating this point of freedom, <hi>vim &amp; majorem, &amp; metum excipio, quibus adhibitis electio perit;</hi> and <hi>Cicero, nec quicquam aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati tam infeſtum eſt, quàm convocati homines, &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mati.</hi> It remaines then we examine, whether the names of many gentlemen were not openly read in tumults; whether they were not poſted, with directions to their particular lodgings; whether the way to the houſe were not ſo beſet with cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marous multitudes, that they muſt paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the midſt of them, whilſt they inform them, what is fit to be voted, and inquire after their names, and what ſide they take. The other two may be reduced to thoſe; It is no wonder many ſtay away, ſince they muſt be abſent even whilſt they are there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Parliament requeſts of the King, that all great Officers of State, by whom publique affaires ſhall be transacted, may be choſen by approbation or nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great Councell: could the King conceive this diſhonourable for him &amp;c. if all Parliaments were not taken as deadly enemies to Royalty?</hi>]</p>
               <p>Is that the reaſon why each man preſerves his own rights, becauſe he takes all the reſt of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49803:56"/>for deadly enemies? Can he with honour confeſſe himſelfe unfit to manage that truſt which the law hath committed to him? with equall reaſon they may challenge to themſelves the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of all Biſhops, Miniſters, Sheriffs, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> and diſpoſe of all the Preferments in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſubſtance of the requeſt ſeemes to be no more but this, that it would pleaſe the King to be adviſed by Parliaments, &amp;c:</hi>] What an affected miſtake is this? He is aſhamed to call it by the true name, and therefore ſtyles that advice, which is properly command, if it be not in His power to reject their counſell, ſeem it never ſo unreaſonable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the King chooſe ſuch a man Treaſurer or Keeper out of His own good liking only, or upon recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a Courtier, here he is deveſted of no power; but if it be upon the recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Parliament, who in all probability can judge better, and are more concerned, this is an emptying himſelfe of Majeſty and deveſting himſelfe of power.</hi>]</p>
               <p>If this will content them, they ſhall have as much power, as He grants to His Courtiers. Counſellors are not names of authority: they are the Princes eares, His eyes, (this relation is neare enough) He ſees, and heares by them: yet they
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49803:57"/>muſt not paſſe their bounds; they muſt be like to the outward ſenſes ſtill, and make a bare repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation; the office of reaſon is peculiar to him; to paſſe judgement thereon: Their information is not alwayes faithfull; he may conſult reaſon, and, by the benefit of that, correct their errour miſrepreſenting an object as crooked, which in it ſelfe is ſtreight.</p>
               <p>If not out of duty to their King, and a juſt ſenſe of His honour, yet out of love to themſelves, and a naturall care of their own ſafety, Subjects are bound in all legall wayes to expreſſe their diſlike of this propoſition. For they muſt expect to ſuffer all thoſe evills which Faction can produce; and what happineſſe can be hoped for in a Kingdome divided in it ſelfe? This were the ready way to kindle a fire in our own bowells, which would firſt break out in the Countyes electing, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the familyes of the gentry by irreconcileable hatred. For it cannot be imagined, but that power will bandy againſt power, and relations againſt relations, to put Sons or Kinſmen into that roade, which only leads unto preferment. Nor would the flames be quenched, but rather burn more fiercely even in the Houſes, (as being pent in a narrow room) to which the inſolency of ſome
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49803:57"/>attaining offices, (to which they are not equall) the ſhame and diſcontents of others repulſed, and the ambition of all would adde continuall fuell. But the greateſt miſery of all is, were their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions never ſo high, we could have but ſlender hopes of redreſſe. Since the prevayling party (jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their own honour) would eaſily maintain the reputation of their choice, and perhaps it would be neceſſary for them to wink one at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He that cannot think it probable, that out of private ends they ſhould ſo farre neglect juſtice and honour, let him only examine, whether in ſome Parliaments moſt known offendours, and active inſtruments in the peoples miſery, by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in with the prevailing ſide, have not been more ſafe then innocency could have made them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are ſeverall degrees of Prerogatives Royall, ſome whereof have greater power of protection, and leſſe of oppreſsion, and ſuch J am most ſtudious of.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Certainly it were to be deſired, we might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the benefits of power, and not be ſubject to the poſsible abuſe thereof. But ſince this cannot be fully provided for, becauſe the ſame hand which is enabled to protect, may injure; the aimes of wiſeſt States have been, not ſo much to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the power (becauſe then they ſhould be
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49803:58"/>likely to ſuffer under a weak Protector) as the will of oppreſſion. The moſt probable means to effect this, is, (after a certain rule is agreed upon, and Lawes are eſtabliſhed, to acquaint a gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, what he ought to doe, in performance of that truſt committed to him) ſo to order his intereſts, that to advance the peoples good ſhall be for the Princes advantage. Subjects will have great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to promiſe to themſelves a full happineſſe from the faithfull diſcharge of his Regall office, to which he is ſo ſtrongly tyed by thoſe bonds of juſtice and profit. This the wiſdom of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors hath provided for in a high degree, and ſo temper'd this governement, that both King, and people, will be joyntly happy, or joyntly miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The ſeverall goods of each forme are here u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited; we have great Democraticall advantages, and yet may avoyd the evills of a popular State, as long as Monarchy is kept up in its due height, and tumultuous inſolent multitudes are not protected from a legall tryall: we have the good of Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, counſell of the beſt experienced (ſuch as have ſtudied nations and men) nor yet are we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the diſeaſe of it, faction amongſt the Nobility. The Counſell of many is profitable, but the reſolve of one is neceſſary. Since they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49803:58"/>looking upon one another as equalls would be very apt to quarrell; for when one contradicts, what another hath adviſed, the debate between them ſeems to be, which is the wiſer man. Their diſcourſes are like ſo many pleadings for honour, and we know what iſſue ſuch ſuites would come to, when the thing in controverſy is ſo highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, if there were not a judge to determine. And this is the benefit of Monarchy; which is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by ſome power proper to the Houſes it cannot degenerate into a tyranny. For how ſhould this enter in? The old lawes (the ſecurity of our libertyes) cannot be taken away till both Houſes give conſent: but grant an illegall, violent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould break in upon us, by what meanes could it be maintained? The King can have no ſupply of money, without the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and without theſe ſinewes his arm would not be ſtrong enough to hold the reines, which ſhould govern that provoked beaſt, the multitude. But He may take it by force, He cannot doe it in perſon, and it is not to be imagined, any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable number of His people, will be active in their owne ſlavery. Beſides what can he propoſe to himſelfe? The people will give more then can be forced from them; ſo he looſes by it, and then how
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49803:59"/>much doth he hazard againſt leſſe then nothing? He hath leaſt reaſon to break the lawes willfully, becauſe he injoyes moſt by them, and experience having ſhew'd the benefit of obſerving them, and the ill of the contrary, He cannot but doubt, the People would fail of their duty, if he doe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of truſt, and caſt of the bond of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if he doe that of Protection. Theſe things duly weighed, render that malice inexcuſeable, which hath long time exerciſed the people with moſt unreaſonable feares, of lands, and liberty, and Religion being in danger; and this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the King's many ſacred Proteſtations to the contrary before God and all the world, and the whole courſe of his proceedings, which evidently tend to the ſecuring all.</p>
               <p>Now I think it doth fully appeare, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that Remonſtrance, laid down by His Majeſty, by way of recapitulation in ſeven poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is moſt juſtly offenſive; being ſuch as doth threaten ruine to both Church, and State, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting us, either to obey the <hi>King,</hi> or ſerve <hi>God</hi> as we ought.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Parliament</hi> has an abſolute indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable power of declaring Law; ſo that all the right of King and People depends upon their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:49803:59"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>This power must reſt in them, or in the King, or in ſome inferior Court, or elſe all ſuits muſt be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and it can no where reſt more ſafely then in Parliament.</hi>]</q>
               <p>The two Houſes are not the Parliament. The ſubject of ſuch power is the intire body, which conſiſts of three eſtates. Some things are cleare and evident in Law, and want no declarer; if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, all the Subjects right would lye in the breſt of the Iudge. If the two Houſes ſhould Vote, younger Brothers ought to inherite by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> could this deſtroy the right of the firſt born?</p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>Parliaments</hi> are bound to no Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Statutes are not binding to them, why then ſhould Preſidents? yet there is no obligation ſtronger then the Justice and Honour of a Parliament.</hi>]</q>
               <p>This is an excellent ground to juſtifie their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence againſt all the world. For if they can make it appeare, they are not bound to keepe any law, no man can accuſe them for the breach of any. What obligation can juſtice lay on them, who by aſtrange vertue of repreſentation, are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of doing wrong. It will become juſtice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when he hath declared what Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49803:60"/>is, I ſhall be able to judge of that bond; it may perchance not ſtand with their honour, not to be able to prove men guilty, after they have once accuſed and impriſoned them. Statutes ſtand in, full force to the two Houſes, as being not voyd, till repealed by a joynt conſent of all the Eſtates.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That they are Parliaments, and may judge of publique neceſſity without the King, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of any thing.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>They may not deſert the King, but being deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the King, when the Kingdome is in distreſſe, they may judge of that diſtreſſe and relieve it, and are to be accompted by the vertue of Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the whole body of the State.</hi>]</q>
               <p>To diſſent, after he hath granted what ever can in reaſon be deſired, is not to deſert the Houſes. Upon pretence of diſtreſſe, to take illegall courſes, is as if they ſhould perſwade us, we are not in health, and therefore they muſt breake our heads to forward our recovery. They repreſent the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſome purpoſes, not the King to any, and therefore are but a part of the State.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That no member of <hi>Parliament</hi> ought to be troubled for Treaſon <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without leave.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>This is intended of ſuſpicion only, and when leave may ſeaſonably be bad, and when competent
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49803:60"/>accuſers appeare not in the impeachment.</hi>]</q>
               <p>If by ſuſpicions be meant only a bare not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in, this in juſtice cannot be ſufficient ground. But upon Articles drawn and proofes in readineſſe, which it is not fit to produce, while the accuſed partyes are at liberty, they may be medled with: for deſignes of this nature may brook no delay, becauſe it might prove dangerous to the King's ſafety, or at leaſt afford them liberty to eſcape. If the Houſes being adjourned were not able to give conſent, or upon too much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſhould not be willing, hath not the Law provided in ſuch a caſe for triall of Treaſon?</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the ſoveraigne power reſides in both Houſes of Parliament, the King having no negative voyce.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>This power is not claimed as ordinary, nor to any purpoſe, but to ſave the Kingdom from ruine, and in caſe where the King is ſo ſeduced, as that be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres dangerous men, and proſequutes his loyall Subjects.</hi>]</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not as ordinary;</hi> that is they will only be King's as long as they pleaſe, and when they are weary of Reigning, the Kingdome ſhall be out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and then it ſhall be his turne to command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>To ſave it from ruine;</hi> the Law hath better
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49803:61"/>provided for the Peoples ſafety, by prohibiting all illegall executions of power, grounded upon what ſpecious pretences ſoever, <hi>And in caſe where the King is ſeduced;</hi> that is, when he is not ſo wiſe as he ſhould be, becauſe he does not think as they doe, and refuſes to ſatisfy the humors, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of ſome. <hi>And prefers;</hi> (this ſeems to be the true cauſe of all; preferments doe not goe the right way) <hi>dangerous men, i. e.</hi> ſuch as deſire he ſhould govern according to the known Lawes of the Land. <hi>And proſequutes his loyall Subjects; i. e.</hi> is driven from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Yorke,</hi> where He long time patiently expected the undeceiving of His People.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That leavying Forces againſt the perſonall commands of the King (though accompanyed with his preſence) is not leavying warre againſt the King: but warr againſt his Authority, though not Perſon, is warre againſt the King.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>If this were not ſo, the Parliament ſeeing a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced King ruining himſelfe and the Kingdom, could not ſave both, but muſt ſtand and look on.</hi>]</q>
               <p>It is againſt common ſenſe to fancy a King rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Himſelfe and Kingdom; He can neither be willing nor able. Upon a mad ſuppoſall, mad conſequences will follow.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49803:61"/>
               <p n="7">7. That according to ſome Parliaments, they may depoſe Kings.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>'Tis denyed that any King was depoſed by a free Parliament fairely elected.</hi>]</q>
               <p>This is moſt certain, but takes not off thoſe words upon which this Propoſition is grounded.</p>
               <p>Theſe might well have been omitted, as being more fully handled in the book. But leaſt he ſhould complaine any thing was paſt over, I choſe by a ſhort review to be his remembrancer. The Propoſitions collected out of His Majeſties Declarations, are but the brief of his <hi>Obſervations,</hi> to all which I have already ſpoken.</p>
               <p>To conclude, if the people hearken to reaſon they muſt needs think, His Majeſty will be more ready to prevent all reall danger, then any Subject whatſoever, becauſe He is ſure to beare the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſhare in the loſſe. It alwaies was the maſter Policy amongſt the wiſeſt Legiſlators to grant to them the greateſt power of government, to whom the preſervation of the preſent ſtate would be moſt beneficiall; becauſe their private intereſts were the ſame with the publique, from which if they ſwarv'd by error or misinformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own diſadvantage did ſoon appeare.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
